<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">DISPUTool 2.0: A Modular Architecture for Multi-Layer Argumentative Analysis of Political Debates</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">3IA Côte d&apos;Azur Investments</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_MfnAGDu">
					<orgName type="full">EU Horizon</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_p6pF84u">
					<orgName type="full">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ANR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">French government</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Pierpaolo</forename><surname>Goffredo</surname></persName>
							<email>goffredo@i3s.unice.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
							<email>elena.cabrio@univ-cotedazur.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Serena</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
							<email>serena.villata@univ-cotedazur.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shohreh</forename><surname>Haddadan</surname></persName>
							<email>shohreh.haddadan@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<address>
									<settlement>Zortify</settlement>
									<country key="LU">Luxembourg</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jhonatan</forename><surname>Torres Sanchez</surname></persName>
							<email>jhonatan.torres-sanchez@univ-cotedazur.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>3IA Techpool</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">DISPUTool 2.0: A Modular Architecture for Multi-Layer Argumentative Analysis of Political Debates</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">EBCD4A3B468B86C82D611EBFA59C2529</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1609/aaai.v37i13.27069</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Political debates are one of the most salient moments of an election campaign, where candidates are challenged to discuss the main contemporary and historical issues in a country. These debates represent a natural ground for argumentative analysis, which has always been employed to investigate political discourse structure and strategy in philosophy and linguistics. In this paper, we present DISPUTool 2.0, an automated tool which relies on Argument Mining methods to analyse the political debates from the US presidential campaigns to extract argument components (i.e., premise and claim) and relations (i.e., support and attack), and highlight fallacious arguments. DISPUTool 2.0 allows also for the automatic analysis of a piece of a debate proposed by the user to identify and classify the arguments contained in the text. A REST API is provided to exploit the tool's functionalities.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Argumentation in political context has been studied since antiquity, and it still raises a continuous inquiry given the challenging topic <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">(Mohammed and Lewinski 2013)</ref>. The design of Digital Humanities frameworks to support historians and social scientists in their investigation of political discourse through (semi-)automatic approaches to identify, classify and analyse such a kind of textual content is a key test-bed for Artificial Intelligence and Natural Language Processing (NLP) methods.</p><p>The issue of analyzing argument structures through NLP methods led to a new research field called Argument(-ation) Mining (AM) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(Cabrio and Villata 2018;</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">Lawrence and Reed 2019)</ref>. AM deals with the ability of identifying argumentative components (e.g., premise, claim, warrant, backing) and predicting their relations (e.g., attack, support, undercut, rebut) in texts to analyze argumentation in various domains.</p><p>In this paper, we present a new version of DISPUTool, a web tool conceived to support humanities scholars in the exploration and evaluation of textual political debates in English <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(Haddadan, Cabrio, and Villata 2019)</ref>. To the best of our knowledge, DISIPUTool 2.0 is the only automated tool which allows to automatically identify and classify argumentative components (i.e., premise and claim) and rela-tions (i.e., attack and support) from the transcripts of political debates in English through AM methods. Despite the plethora of existing AM approaches and annotated corpora, very few of them apply AM to political text, and none of them addresses the issue of mining full argument structures from such texts, supporting intelligent data exploration, as in DISPUTool 2.0. More precisely, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Menini et al. 2018)</ref> predict relations but in a different setup (i.e., speeches in monological form). <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">(Lippi and Torroni 2016)</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">(Naderi and Hirst 2015)</ref> focus on predicting argument relations only. <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(Duthie and Budzynska 2018)</ref> apply methods to mine ethos arguments from UK parliamentary debates, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(Visser et al. 2020</ref>) present a corpus from the political scenario annotated with the Inference Anchoring Theory <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(Budzynska and Reed 2011)</ref>, to extract propositional structures anchored on the speakers' locutions.</p><p>DISPUTool 2.0 Main Functionalities DISPUTool 2.0 allows exploring the official transcripts of the televised presidential debates in the US from 1960 until 2016, from the website of the Commission on Presidential Debates (CPD)<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . It gives also tho possibility to automatically analyze political debates from the argumentative point of view, trained on the official transcripts of these debates. More specifically, the functionalities of DISPUTool are the followings:</p><p>US Presidential Debate Argumentative Analysis. It is possible to explore the corpus made of 39 US presidential debates annotated with argumentative components and relations. When the user selects one of the debates, three argumentative elements are shown: i) the argumentative components are highlighted in the textual arguments put forward by each candidate, and a label 'claim' or 'premise' is associated to these pieces of text (as in DISPUTool 1.0); ii) the relations holding between the identified components are identified and labeled to indicate whether it is a support or an attack relation, and iii) fallacious arguments are highlighted in the text and associated to one of the following 6 classes of fallacies: ad hominem, appeal to authority, appeal to emotion, false cause, slogan, slippery slope <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(Goffredo et al. 2022</ref>). The last two points are peculiar of DISPUTool 2.0. Named Entity Recognition for Political Debates. The user can search for the Named Entities (NEs) the system identifies, using the Stanford Named Entity Recognizer<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> with the possibility to filter the results based on the type of NE (e.g., religion, location, organization, nationality, and person), on the year of the debate, and on the speaker.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experimental Setting and Results</head><p>DISPUTool is trained on the ElecDeb60To16 dataset<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> . The overall new architecture of DISPUTool 2.0<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> is visualized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.</p><p>Argument Component Detection. For the argumentative analysis, we adopt the architecture of <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(Mayer, Cabrio, and Villata 2020)</ref>. We cast the argument component detection task as a sequence tagging problem, using the BIO-tagging scheme for the pre-trained bidirectional transformer language model <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(Mayer et al. 2021)</ref>. Thus, the token-level representation of contextualized sentences is computed by the BERT base model <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(Devlin et al. 2018)</ref>, fine-tuned during 15 epochs with an Adam optimizer, a learning rate of 6e-5 and a maximum sentence length of 64. The sentence representation is passed into a Recurrent Neural Network, i.e., a Gated Recurrent Unit (GRU <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(Cho et al. 2014)</ref>) and then into a Conditional Random Field (CRF <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">(Lafferty, McCallum, and Pereira 2001)</ref>). The dataset splits are 80% for the train set, and 10% for the validation and test set, respectively. The obtained f1-score on the test set is 0.79.</p><p>Relation Prediction. For the relation prediction task, the sequence classification problem jointly models the relations by classifying all the argumentative component combinations using a bidirectional transformer architecture. Thus, the linear layer with a softmax manages this new representation which allows classifying the identified relations into three target classes (i.e., Support, Attack and NoRelation). The base model used with pre-trained weights for the sentence representation is RoBERTa <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(Liu et al. 2019)</ref>, then finetuned with a learning rate of 6e-5, batch size of 8, maximum sentence length of 64 sub-words tokens per input example during 15 epochs. We take into consideration the weight factor of the 3 classes<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">5</ref> in the weighted Cross Entropy Loss, normalizing the number of training samples of this class. These settings achieve a macro f1-score of 0.60 on the test set.</p><p>DISPUTool 2.0 API To foster versatility and re-usability, we also enhance DISPUTool 2.0 such that each of the processing step (e.g., argument component detection and relation prediction) can be executed as independent units via our public available REST API.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concluding Remarks</head><p>In this paper, we presented DISPUTool 2.0, a tool which allows to automatically analyse political debates from the argumentation perspective (components, relations, and fallacies). In addition to the visual exploration of the training dataset of US presidential debates, DISPUTool allows the user to analyse her own political debate to identify the underlying argumentative structure.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: DISPUTool 2.0 new pipeline based on transformer models.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,54.00,54.00,503.99,199.54" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>www.debates.orgThe Thirty-Seventh AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence </p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://nlp.stanford.edu/software/CRF-NER.html</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://github.com/pierpaologoffredo/disputool2.0/tree/main/ Dataset/ElecDeb60To16</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>https://3ia-demos.inria.fr/disputool/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>Due to an high level of unbalancing, we also undersampled the most represented label, i.e., NoRelation.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This work was partly supported by the <rs type="funder">French government</rs>, through the <rs type="funder">3IA Côte d'Azur Investments</rs> in the Future project managed by the <rs type="funder">National Research Agency (ANR)</rs> with the reference number <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-19-P3IA-0002</rs>. This work was partly supported also by <rs type="funder">EU Horizon</rs> <rs type="programName">2020</rs> project <rs type="projectName">AI4Media</rs>, under contract no. <rs type="grantNumber">951911</rs> (https://ai4media.eu/).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_p6pF84u">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-19-P3IA-0002</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_MfnAGDu">
					<idno type="grant-number">951911</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">AI4Media</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">2020</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Whence inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Budzynska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Dundee</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Five Years of Argument Mining: a Data-driven Analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Seventh International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2018)</title>
		<meeting>the Twenty-Seventh International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2018)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="5427" to="5433" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Learning phrase representations using RNN encoderdecoder for statistical machine translation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Cho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Van Merriënboer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Gulcehre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Bahdanau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bougares</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schwenk</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Bengio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1406.1078</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Devlin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M.-W</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Toutanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1810.04805</idno>
		<title level="m">Bert: Pre-training of deep bidirectional transformers for language understanding</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A Deep Modular RNN Approach for Ethos Mining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Duthie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Budzynska</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-Seventh International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2018)</title>
		<meeting>the Twenty-Seventh International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2018)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4041" to="4047" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Fallacious Argument Classification in Political Debates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Goffredo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haddadan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Vorakitphan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirty-First International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2022)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Raedt</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting>the Thirty-First International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2022)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4143" to="4149" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>ijcai.org</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DISPUTool-A tool for the Argumentative Analysis of Political Debates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Haddadan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 28th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2019)</title>
		<title level="s">International Joint Conferences on Artificial Intelligence Organization</title>
		<meeting>the 28th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence (IJCAI 2019)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="6524" to="6526" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Conditional random fields: Probabilistic models for segmenting and labeling sequence data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lafferty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mccallum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Pereira</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Eighteenth International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2001)</title>
		<meeting>the Eighteenth International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML 2001)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argument Mining: A Survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lawrence</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Comput. Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="765" to="818" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argument mining from speech: Detecting claims in political debates</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lippi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Torroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2016)</title>
		<meeting>the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2016)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Ott</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Goyal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Du</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Levy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lewis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zettlemoyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Stoyanov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1907.11692</idno>
		<title level="m">Roberta: A robustly optimized bert pretraining approach</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transformerbased argument mining for healthcare applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 24th European Conference on Artificial Intelligenc (ECAI 2020)</title>
		<meeting>the 24th European Conference on Artificial Intelligenc (ECAI 2020)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IOS Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2108" to="2115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enhancing evidence-based medicine with natural language argumentative analysis of clinical trials</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Mayer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Marro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Artificial Intelligence in Medicine</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">118</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">102098</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Never Retreat, Never Retract: Argumentation Analysis for Political Speeches</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Menini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Cabrio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Tonelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Villata</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirty-Second AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2018)</title>
		<meeting>the Thirty-Second AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2018)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="4889" to="4896" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argumentation in political deliberation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lewinski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Argumentation in Context</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="9" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argumentation mining in parliamentary discourse</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Naderi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Hirst</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Principles and practice of multiagent systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Argumentation in the 2016 US presidential elections: annotated corpora of television debates and social media reaction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Visser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Konat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Duthie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Koszowy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Budzynska</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lang. Resour. Evaluation</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="123" to="154" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
