<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A Model for Meteorological Knowledge Graphs: Application to Météo-France Data</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadia</forename><forename type="middle">Yacoubi</forename><surname>Ayadi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7271)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7271)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7271)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fabien</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7271)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">UMR 7271)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A Model for Meteorological Knowledge Graphs: Application to Météo-France Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">0D9AE9353C5E6261C2EABB153BECD4FD</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Knowledge Graph</term>
					<term>Semantic Modelling</term>
					<term>Observational Data</term>
					<term>Linked Data</term>
					<term>Meteorology</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>To study and predict meteorological phenomenons and to include them in broader studies, the ability to represent and exchange meteorological data is of paramount importance. A typical approach in integrating and publishing such data now is to formalize a knowledge graph relying on Linked Data and semantic Web standard models and practices. In this paper, we first discuss the semantic modelling issues related to spatio-temporal data such as meteorological observational data. We motivate the reuse of a network of existing ontologies to define a semantic model in which meteorological parameters are semantically defined, described and integrated. The model is generic enough to be adopted and extended by meteorological data providers to publish and integrate their sources while complying with Linked Data principles. Finally, we present a meteorological knowledge graph of weather observations based on our proposed model, published in the form of an RDF dataset, that we produced by transforming observation records made by Météo-France weather stations. It covers a large number of meteorological variables described through spatial and temporal dimensions and thus has the potential to serve several scientific case studies from different domains including agriculture, agronomy, environment, climate change and natural disasters.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Meteorological data have attracted great interest in recent years since they are crucial for many application domains. Meteorological observations typically include measurements of several weather parameters such as wind direction and speed, air pressure, rainfall, humidity and temperature. However, these data are mostly collected and stored separately in different files using a tabular data format that lacks explicit semantics, which impedes their integration and sharing to serve researchers from different domains such as agriculture, climate change studies or natural disaster monitoring. Publishing such data on the Web using Linked Data (LD) principles would make them more accessible, easier to discover and reuse. However, integrating and interpreting weather data requires rich metadata about studied features of interest such as the air, observed properties such as the temperature or the humidity, the utilized sampling strategy, the specific location of a weather station and the time (instant or interval) at which the property was measured, and a variety of other information. Getting insights into these heterogeneous data motivates the need of a semantic model in which domain-specific ontologies play a central role by providing a coherent view over it.</p><p>In this paper, we propose a semantic model that relies on a network of modular ontologies and domain vocabularies that capture common and specific characteristics of observational meteorological data at a fine grained level, including time, location, provenance, units of measurement, etc. We paid specific attention to propose a model that adheres to LD best practices and standards, thereby allowing for its re-use and extension by other meteorological data producers, and making it accommodated for multiple application domains. To deal with the complexity of the domain knowledge to be modelled, we adopt the SAMOD agile methodology <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> for ontology development, consisting of small steps within an iterative process that focuses on creating well-developed and documented models by using significant exemplar data so as to produce semantic models that are always ready-to-use and easily-understandable by humans. Based on the early work of Uschold &amp; Gruninger <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> the SAMOD process is initiated by a motivating scenario that leads to a set of competency questions that, in turn, provide requirements on the knowledge graph model. We build a self-contained semantic model reusing and extending standard ontologies, among which the GeoSPARQL ontology for spatial features and relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the Time ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for temporal entities and relations, the Sensor, Observation, Sample, and Actuator (SOSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Semantic Sensor Network (SSN) ontologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for sensors and observations, and the RDF Data Cube ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> for aggregation and multidimensionality features.</p><p>Furthermore, we implement and make available a software pipeline that is reproducible to generate knowledge graphs compliant with the proposed semantic model. We use the pipeline to generate the first release of the WeKG-MF RDF knowledge graph constructed according to this model from open weather observations published by Météo-France. It includes weather observations from January 2019 till December 2021. To demonstrate the interest of WeKG-MF and the underlying semantic model, competency questions identified in our use case were translated into SPARQL queries to retrieve data from the WeKG-MF knowledge graph in order to meet expert requirements.</p><p>The paper is structured as follows. Section 2 describes a motivating scenario that allows us to identify a set of competency questions. Section 3 details our semantic model and highlights its design principles. Section 4 presents the RDF-based knowledge graph constructed from the observational weather data archives of Météo-France. Section 5 presents a validation of the proposed model and the constructed knowledge graph through a set of SPARQL queries implementing the competency questions identified in our motivating scenario. Section 6 presents the related work on lifting meteorological data into RDF datasets. Finally, we conclude and present perspectives of our work in Section 7.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Motivating Scenario and Competency Questions</head><p>In this section, we present a motivating scenario <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> inspired from requirements expressed by experts and collected in the context of the D2KAB French research project <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . The primary objective of D2KAB is to create a framework to turn agriculture, agronomy and biodiversity data into semantically described, interoperable, actionable, and open knowledge. Experts in agronomy investigate the correlations between the development rate of plants and weather parameters. They are especially interested in comparing aggregated values of a weather parameter for the same period of time in the same geographic location across years, e.g. the Growing Daily Degrees (GDD) calculated from the daily average air temperature minus a certain threshold called base temperature. This motivating scenario already triggers competency questions that reflect the requirements on the knowledge that has to be represented in the proposed semantic model as well as the way of scoping and delimiting it <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. We present some of them in the following:</p><p>CQ1. What is the measurement unit of a given weather parameter? Several parameters such as atmospheric pressure, air temperature, wind speed, relative humidity, sea surface temperature are measured using different sensors and procedures, and the resulting numeric/qualitative values are included in weather reports. Measurement units and possible values for qualitative parameters are not included in these reports and are usually documented in external sources (e.g., WMO documentations).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CQ2</head><p>. At what time of the day was the highest value of a weather parameter measured (observed)? Temporal features are crucial for observational data. Indeed, within a 24-hour time interval, sensors hosted by weather stations regularly produce different measurement values for the same weather parameter.</p><p>CQ3. What is the closest weather station to a specific spatial location? This competency question points to the fact that the semantic model should encompass a spatial module to capture the geographic coordinates of stations by means of longitude and latitude values.</p><p>CQ4. For a specific location and given a calendar interval, provide time series of some aggregated (pre-computed) weather parameters. Providing aggregated data over relevant time period and for a specific location/weather station is a recurrent need. For instance, daily minimum, maximum and mean temperature, cumulative rainfall during a period of time for each station are examples of significant aggregated parameters for different studies in agronomy or climate change studies. According to CQ1 and CQ2, weather parameters as well as their significance need to be clearly expressed and formalized. Metadata describing weather properties such as their possible lexical labels in different languages and their possible measurement units are required. CQ4 is one example of competency questions that require the computation of aggregated values (sum of average temperatures, weekly average temperature). This motivated us to propose a semantic model presented in 3 that combines SSN/SOSA ontologies and RDF data cube vocabulary to represent inherent semantics of observations at different levels of semantic granularity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Semantic Model</head><p>Our aim is to design a semantic model in which meteorological variables are semantically defined, described and integrated. The analysis of CQs presented in section 2 led us to select a set of state-of-the art ontologies and thesauri to be re-used. It includes:</p><p>the SOSA/SSN ontologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> designed for describing sensors and their observations, and that we extend with new classes to capture the semantics of meteorological observations and provide formal definitions of these new classes. The extension is motivated by the re-use of the Value Sets ontology design pattern; the Time Ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> for describing the temporal properties of our data; the QUDT ontology and vocabulary <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> representing the various quantity and unit standards and supporting their processing such as conversion; the GeoSPARQL vocabulary <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for representing spatial information in our data; the RDF data Cube Vocabulary <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> supporting the publication of multi-dimensional data, such as statistics. We use it to create spatio-temporal slices of meteorological observations by fixing time spans and geographic places as well as applying aggregation functions; SOSA/SSN ontologies only support the description of a single, atomic, observation.</p><p>The OWL formalization of our model as well as the related SKOS vocabulary are available in our Github repository<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> . The prefixes of ontologies and vocabularies reused or introduced in this paper are listed in the repository's README <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> .</p><p>In the following we present in details our model according to four categories of features: features of interest, spatial features, temporal features, and aggregated features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Features of Interest and Observable Properties: Describing Observations</head><p>In order to propose a self-contained model for representing and publishing meteorological data, we define three new classes. weo:MeteorologicalObservation is the core class of our model; it supports the description of a single, atomic observation. A meteorological observation is related to a particular feature of interest, instance of class weo:Meteoro logicalFeature, and an observable property, instance of class weo:WeatherProperty. These three classes specialize classes from the SOSA/SSN ontologies as reflected by their formal definitions. weo:MeteorologicalFeature is defined as a subclass of sosa:FeatureOfInterest and serves to represent meteorological features of interest, that is phenomena or events such as precipitations, gusts or storms. Formally, the class is defined as follows:  Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> depicts the RDF graph representing an example meteorological observation relative to the wind feature of interest and reporting the average wind speed observable property. Although SOSA/SSN ontologies are commonly used to represent knowledge about sensor data across domains, the definition of observable properties and features of interest, as well as their alignment with existing controlled vocabularies, are delegated to the community of interest. Thus, we have reused the Value Sets<ref type="foot" target="#foot_3">4</ref> (VS) ontology design pattern and we defined a SKOS<ref type="foot" target="#foot_4">5</ref> vocabulary whose concepts are instances of weo:WeatherProperty and weo:MeteorologicalFeature and represent the possible observable properties and features of interest. This SKOS vocabulary is available on our Github repository <ref type="foot" target="#foot_5">6</ref> .</p><p>An excerpt of it is given in Listing 1.1. The SKOS concepts representing weather properties are aligned with both terms from the NERC Climate and Forecast Standard Names vocabulary and terms from the QUDT Quantity Kind vocabulary that includes general concepts about quantifiable quantities such as quantity-kind:Speed or quantitykind:Temperature. For instance, wevp:averageWindSpeed and wevp:gustSpeed are declared as narrower than qudt-kind:Speed (and instances of class qudt:QuantityKind). The vocabulary can be easily extended to include new observable properties and features as long as it is compliant with the proposed semantic model.</p><p>wevf : wind a weo : MeteorologicalFeature , skos : Concept ; rdfs : label " wind " @en , " vent " @fr ; ssn : hasProperty wevp : windAverageSpeed , wevp : w in d A v e r a g eD i r e c t i o n .</p><p>wevp : windAverageSpeed a weo : WeatherProperty , qudt : QuantityKind , skos : Concept ; ssn : isPropertyOf wevf : wind ; skos : broader nerc : CFSN0038 , &lt; http :// qudt . org /2.1/ vocab / quantitykind / Speed &gt;; qudt : applicableUnit &lt; http :// qudt . org / vocab / unit /M -PER -SEC &gt; ; skos : prefLabel " Vitesse moyenne du vent 10 mn " @fr ," Average wind speed 10 mn " @en ; wep : hasAbbreviation " ff ".</p><p>Listing Observation results are literals and an observation is linked to its result by a property sosa:hasSimpleResult. Instead of repeating the measurement units within each observation, we denote it at the level of the SKOS concept representing the observable property in our vocabulary (Listing 1.1). Furthermore, some qualitative weather properties require the use of standard encoded values defined by the WMO. For instance, the ground state is a weather property whose possible values (dry, moist, etc.) are in a predefined set of values of the WMO 0901 code <ref type="foot" target="#foot_6">7</ref> . For each qualitative weather properties, we created a skos:Collection whose members represent the possible values of the weather property as described in the WMO documentation. Listing 1.2 presents an excerpt of the skos:Collection of values for the state of the ground weather property.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Spatial Features: Locating the Weather Stations</head><p>A weather station typically hosts sensors and equipments for the purpose of measuring atmospheric conditions and providing information for weather forecasts. Whereas a description of sensors and equipment is not always made available by meteorological data providers, relevant metadata about weather stations generally include station identifier, name, latitude, longitude and altitude. Our model introduces the weo:WeatherStation class to represent any type of weather station. To capture stations' spatial location, weo:WeatherStation is introduced as a subclass of geosparql:Feature. Therefore, each instance of weo:WeatherStation has a geometry that is a point with specific coordinates. Following GeoSPARQL vocabulary, geo-coordinates of a weather station are defined as a Well-Known Text (WKT) literal (e.g., POINT(8.792667 41.918)). Our adoption of GeoSPARQL is motivated by the fact that it allows to efficiently query spatial data based on a set of spatial functions. It enables us to express spatial queries involving meteorological data, e.g. retrieving the closest station to a given location or the precipitations for a specific location. We also reused latitude, longitude, and altitude datatype properties from the WGS84 vocabulary since WKT literals do not integrate information about the altitude of a station.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Temporal Features: Defining Time Entities</head><p>In many cases, the observation of a given weather property is made over a period of time. The duration of a measurement varies depending on the property. For such cases, we reuse the sosa:phenomenonTime property to link an instance of weo:Meteorological-Observation to an instance of time:Interval. Since time durations are described in the documentation of weather observed properties, we defined different time interval classes by expressing an OWL restriction on their duration that may be declared in seconds, minutes or hours. The interest of doing this is that these time intervals are declared once in our model and are reused for all observations, and thus avoid substantial redundancy. For instance, in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> the wevp:windAverageSpeed weather property is measured during a period of 10 minutes. This is denoted by property sosa:phenomenonTime whose value is an instance of class weo:Interval10m, while the end time of the interval is an instance of class time:Instant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4">Aggregated Features: Defining Observation Slices</head><p>Observations produced by sensors can rapidly reach enormous volumes. The CQ4 competency question (see Section 2) stresses the need to create focused and homogeneous sets of observations that share some dimension. In particular, creating times series of air temperatures or other weather parameters is a recurrent need. In this respect, we reuse the RDF Data Cube vocabulary (DCV) <ref type="foot" target="#foot_7">8</ref> to describe multi-dimensional data according to a 'data cube' model. Each data cube is an instance of class qb:DataSet and is linked to instances of class qb:DataStructureDefinition by property qb:structure (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>). A Data Structure Definition (DSD) defines the structure of a data cube and how observations are linked to the measures and dimensions of the data cube. Listing 1.3 presents an example of DSD wes:annualTimeSeriesTemperature that defines the structure of a data cube of air temperatures. According to this DSD, each observation contains three daily measures: the minimum, maximum and average temperatures. The qb:Slice class enables to represent a subset of observations that share the same dimensions. In our model, we declare spatio-temporal slices of observations by fixing the spatial and temporal dimensions: the spatial dimension may refer to the weather station, while the temporal dimension corresponds to a calendar interval. While the SOSA/SSN ontologies only support the description of a single, atomic, meteorological observation, an observation (instance of qb:Observation) in a spatio-temporal slice is represented by a set of measures (instances of qb:MeasureProperty) each linked to an observable property (declared in our SKOS vocabulary) with property qb:concept. Furthermore, observations from the same qb:Slice have attributes such as the observation date that refers to a 24-hour interval during which a certain value of a certain parameter is selected with respect to a specific condition or aggregation (e.g. maximum daily temperature).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Météo-France Weather Observations RDF Dataset</head><p>This section presents the pipeline that we set up to lift the observation reports published by Météo-France into an RDF knowledge graph named WeKG-MF (Weather Knowledge Graph -Météo-France), that complies with the model presented in Section 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Météo-France Dataset</head><p>In France, the primary source of weather data and forecasting is the Météo-France<ref type="foot" target="#foot_8">9</ref> organisation. As a member of World Meteorological Organization (WMO) <ref type="foot" target="#foot_9">10</ref> , Météo-France provides access to daily meteorological observations. These data are the result of measurements performed by 62 weather stations located in different regions in metropolitan France and overseas departments. Measurements are generated by different sensors/equipments hosted by weather stations, collected in daily tabular data files such as the table presented in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">3</ref>. Each line corresponds to the values of meteorological parameters measured or observed at a given weather station (column 1) at a specific date and time (column 2). For instance, column u denotes the values of "relative air humidity" measured at different times of the day at different &lt; http :// ns . inria . fr / meteo / dataset -MF /2021 &gt; a qb : DataSet ; qd : structure wes : a n n u a l T i m e S e r i e s T e m p e r a t u r e ; dct : title " French Meterological Weather Data of 2021" @en ; dct : description " Daily min / max / avg temperature in 2021" @en .  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Lifting Process</head><p>We downloaded from Météo-France's portal <ref type="foot" target="#foot_10">11</ref> the list of SYNOP <ref type="foot" target="#foot_11">12</ref> weather stations in Geo-JSON format <ref type="foot" target="#foot_12">13</ref> , and the monthly observation reports generated by these stations as CSV files. Measurement are generated every 3 hours and disseminated into the WMO network in less than 15 minutes. Then, we implemented a reproducible software pipeline to generate WeKG-MF in compliance with the proposed model. The core of the pipeline is the mapping task that is performed with Morph-xR2RML tool 14 , an implementation of the xR2RML mapping language <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> for MongoDB databases. Pipeline scripts as well as xr2RML mapping triples are available in our github repository <ref type="foot" target="#foot_13">15</ref> . Additionally, we enriched the weather stations' descriptions by linking each station to the closest Wikidata entity, based on its geographic coordinates, using property dct:spatial. This allows us to get further information about the regions, departments and municipalities in which weather stations are located using simple SPARQL queries. Furthermore, leveraging Wikidata allows to benefit from its many links to other data sources, in particular the French national institute for statistics and economic studies (INSEE) which is highly used and trusted by French organisms.</p><p>WeKG-MF is published under an open licence, is assigned a DOI <ref type="foot" target="#foot_14">16</ref> and can be downloaded from Zenodo. In the short term, we intend to make it available through a public SPARQL endpoint.The current version of WeKG-MF covers the period from January 2019 to November 2021. Statistics about its content are provided in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">1</ref>. The validation process is intended to check the consistency of the model and its ability to address requirements and cover the domain <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. In Section 2, we have presented an example motivating scenario that pointed to a set of competency questions which reflect requirements that potential users may want to get answers for. In this section, we evaluate the proposed semantic model by demonstrating how CQs can be translated into SPARQL queries. Note that the model and the WeKG-MF dataset were loaded in a Virtuoso triple store deployed as a Docker image.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Querying Low-Level Observations</head><p>Let us first address CQ2 "At what time was the highest value of a weather parameter measured (observed)?". It points to the need to query the exact time at which a given parameter reaches which varies from a crop to another. Note that daily average temperature corresponds to the average of the minimum and maximum temperatures measured during a 24-hour interval. Listing 1.6 shows the SPARQL query formalizing competency question CQ4 and shows it can easily calculate GDD values based on pre-calculated slices corresponding to a specific weather station and by selecting beginning date of a calendar interval. Note that the value of 10 in the query denotes an example of base temperature. Without pre-calculated slices, CQ4 could be implemented by a SPARQL query that computes min/max/avg temperatures for a specific weather station on the fly. However, the complexity of the writing of the query as well as its execution time would be significantly higher. The generation of spatio-temporal slices is done once and they can be reused for the calculation of any new aggregated parameters and facilitates their implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Implemented Notebook and Visualizations</head><p>We developed a set of SPARQL queries available on the Github repository of our project 17 , together with a Jupyter Notebook that demonstrate how the results of SPARQL queries can be used to generate visualizations from the WeKG-MF knowledge graph. As an example, Figure <ref type="figure">4</ref> presents different types of data visualisations. The first plot (on the top-left) shows daily cumulative precipitations measured at the "Bordeaux-Merignac" station and the second one (on the top-right) shows the evolution of daily average temperature collected from weather stations located in the French region of "Nouvelle Aquitaine". Both plots show a comparison of aggregated values calculated based on two weather parameters (precipitation and air temperatures) available in the WeKG-MF knowledge graph. The third visualisation (on the bottom-center) shows the different weather stations located in Metropolitan France.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Related Work</head><p>In this section, we present existing research works on the publication of meteorological data as LOD datasets. First, the AEMET meteorological dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> makes available some data sources from the Spanish Meteorological Office through a SPARQL endpoint. The dataset is based on the AEMET ontology network which follows a modular structure: a central ontology reports into RDF data. In our work, we are interested not only in describing observational data but also in transforming them into semantically-enriched observations accessible via SPARQL queries in order to enable their integration in a wide range of applications from different domains such as agronomy or natural disaster monitoring.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Conclusion and Future Works</head><p>Meteorological observations refer to values of different weather observable properties measured across space and time by means of different sensors and equipment available in weather stations. Transforming these data into RDF knowledge graphs bridges the semantic gap between observational data and other resources also published on the Web as Linked Open Data, thus enabling their re-use in different domain applications. In terms of sustainability, we provide a fully automatic pipeline that enables us the update of the WeKG-MF graph over time with new weather data downloaded from Météo-France.</p><p>Towards this goal, in this paper we proposed a reusable and extensible model that semantically describes the multiple dimensions behind meteorological data. Our semantic model reuses the SOSA/SSN ontologies and extends it with new classes about specific feature of interest entities. These classes are rigorously defined and aligned with third-party vocabularies and ontologies. We rely on Time Ontology and GeoSPARQL to capture the spatio-temporal context surrounding observational data, as well as the QUDT schema and vocabulary to include metadata about measurement units of observed weather properties. We leverage the RDF Data Cube vocabulary to create slices of weather parameters that are the result of aggregation functions over spatial and temporal dimensions. This is typically needed to represent time series of min/max/average temperatures or precipitations in a given spatial area. We also propose a SKOS vocabulary of observable properties and features aligned with existing controlled vocabularies. In addition, we generated and published WeKG-MF, an RDF knowledge graph complying with this semantic model, from Météo-France meteorological data observations. To the best of our knowledge, our research work is the first that proposes a meteorological RDF-based knowledge graph.</p><p>This work was started in the context of the D2KAB French project<ref type="foot" target="#foot_18">20</ref> . Within this project, a use case concerns the design and development of a reading interface for the Plant Health Bulletins (PHB) that are meant to inform bio-vigilance stakeholders about the status of plant diseases and crop pests in French regions. This interface shall be able to augment reading experience by integrating related information likely to provide the reader with enriched context and insights into the data they are currently reading. Various related information may be involved, such as phenological stages of crops and pests, phenotyping information, taxonomic resources, geographic references and meteorological observations record history. In the latter, we typically expect the aggregated data (such as max/min/avg temperature or precipitation and the measure of Growing Daily Degrees) to be of utmost importance for experts to draw hypotheses about, e.g., the possible impact of weather conditions on the advent of crop pests at different periods or phenological stages.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Example meteorological observation of the WindAverageSpeed weather property</figDesc><graphic coords="6,134.77,180.66,353.15,188.65" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Fig. 2. Example of an RDF data Cube slice representing a TimeSeries of Air Temperatures</figDesc><graphic coords="9,138.96,115.83,337.44,200.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Listing 1 . 3 .</head><label>13</label><figDesc>wes : a n n u a l T i m e S e r i e s T e m p e r a t u r e a qb : DataStructureDefinition , qb4st : SpatioTemporalDSD ; qb : component [ qb : dimension wes -dimension : year ; qb : co mp o ne nt At t ac hm en t qb : DataSet ] , [ qb : dimension wes -dimension : station ; qb : c om p on en tA t ta ch me n t qb : Slice ] , [ qb : measure wes -measure : m in Da i ly Te mp e ra tu re ] , [ qb : measure wes -measure : m ax Da i ly Te mp e ra tu re ] , [ qb : measure wes -measure : a vg Da i ly Te mp e ra tu re ] , [ qb : attribute wes -attribute : observationDate ] ; qb : sliceKey wes : S l i c e B y S t a t i o n A n d Y e a r . wes -dimension : station a rdf : Property , qb : DimensionProperty ; rdfs : range weo : WeatherStation . wes -dimension : year a rdf : Property , qb : DimensionProperty ; rdfs : range xsd : gYear . wes -measure : minDailyTemp a rdf : Property , qb : MeasureProperty ; rdfs : label " Daily Minimum Temperature " @en ; rdfs : range xsd : decimal ; qb : concept wevp : minAirTemperature . The wes:annualTimeSeriesTemperature Structure Definition.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig. 3. Snapshot of a CSV file of meteorological parameters</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1.1. SKOS representation of meteorological feature wind and related weather property win-dAverageSpeed.</figDesc><table><row><cell>@prefix : &lt; http :// ns . inria . fr / meteo / vocab / weatherproperty / wmocode / &gt; .</cell></row><row><cell>:0901 a skos : Collection ;</cell></row><row><cell>rdfs : label " State of ground without snow or ice cover " @en ;</cell></row><row><cell>skos : member :0901/0 , :0901/1 , ... ;</cell></row><row><cell>:0901/0 a skos : Concept ; rdf : value 0 ;</cell></row><row><cell>skos : definition " Surface of ground dry ( without cracks and no appreciable</cell></row><row><cell>amount of dust or loose sand )".</cell></row></table><note><p><p>:0901/1 a skos : Concept ; rdf : value 1; skos : definition " Surface of ground moist " .</p>Listing 1.2. SKOS collection representing the state of ground qualitative weather property (0901 WMO code).</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>key statistics of the WeKG-MF dataset 5 Validation: Implementing the Competency Questions</figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell><cell>Resources</cell></row><row><cell>Total Nr. of triples</cell><cell>60.601.248</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of classes</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of weather stations</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of Observations for 2019</cell><cell>2.788.528</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of Observations for 2020</cell><cell>2.789.574</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Nr. of Observations for 2021 (till November 2021) 2.528.467</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of weather properties</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of meteorological features</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of Observations per observed property</cell><cell>≈ 405.328</cell></row><row><cell>Nr. of Air Temperatures slices</cell><cell>183</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://www.d2kab.org/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://github.com/Wimmics/d2kab/tree/main/meteo/ontology</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://github.com/Wimmics/d2kab/tree/main/meteo</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3"><p>https://www.w3.org/TR/swbp-specified-values/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4"><p>https://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_5"><p>https://github.com/Wimmics/d2kab/blob/main/meteo/ontology/features-properties-vocabulaire.ttl</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_6"><p>https://epic.awi.de/id/eprint/29967/1/WMO2011i.pdf</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_7"><p>https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-data-cube/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="9" xml:id="foot_8"><p>https://www.meteofrance.com/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="10" xml:id="foot_9"><p>https://public.wmo.int/en/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="11" xml:id="foot_10"><p>https://donneespubliques.meteofrance.fr/?fond=produit&amp;id_produit=90&amp;id_rubrique=32</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="12" xml:id="foot_11"><p>SYNOP: surface synoptic observations, a numerical code used for reporting observations made by weather stations.</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="13" xml:id="foot_12"><p>https://donneespubliques.meteofrance.fr/donnees_libres/Txt/Synop/postesSynop.json</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="15" xml:id="foot_13"><p>https://github.com/Wimmics/d2kab/tree/main/meteo/Lifting-dataset</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="16" xml:id="foot_14"><p>https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5925413</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="18" xml:id="foot_15"><p>http://aemet.linkeddata.es/sparql</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="19" xml:id="foot_16"><p>Last attempt on February, 7th</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2022" xml:id="foot_17"><p></p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="20" xml:id="foot_18"><p>https://www.d2kab.org/</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Listing 1.5. SPARQL query implementing CQ3 its peak. Our model captures the importance of temporal features surrounding observational data by capturing the exact time at which each and every observation is generated. The SPARQL query, presented in Listing 1.5, is a formal translation of CQ2 that allows us to retrieve, for each station available in the WeKG-MF dataset, at what time the maximum air temperature was reached on August 1st, 2021. It shows that CQ2 can be successfully converted and executed as a SPARQL query over the dataset. Another set of SPARQL queries leveraging spatial GeoSPARQL functions demonstrate how end-users can query meteorological observations based on geospatial coordinates of weather stations. For instance, CQ3 expresses the need to query the closest weather station given specific geospatial coordinates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">Querying Observation Slices</head><p>Let us now address the CQ4 "For a specific location and given a calendar interval, provide time series of some aggregated weather parameters?". This question motivates our adoption of the RDF Data Cube Vocabulary to represent pre-calculated time series of aggregated weather parameters. For example, in agronomy, experts are interested in calculating GDD values that are calculated based on the average daily temperature minus a base temperature relates a set of ontologies that describe different sub-domains involved in the modeling of meteorological measurements. These sub-domains are: (meteorological) Measurements, Sensors, Time and Location. As an attempt to access to the dataset, we tried to quey the AEMET SPARQL endpoint 18 , however, we noticed that the endpoint is no longer available 19 . The authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref> present an RDF dataset of meteorological measurements made by a weather station located at the Irstea experimental farm. Our proposition is in line with their work as we rely on most of the ontologies that they used (SOSA/SSN, GeoSPARQL, QUDT, OWL-Time ontology). Yet, we adopt somehow different design principles to propose a minimal yet extensible semantic model for meteorological data. Furthermore, we extend their work to support the description and dynamic generation of homogeneous slices of observations pre-calculated using aggregation functions over temporal and spatial dimensions. Thus, we are able to represent annual times series of daily min, max and average temperatures for each weather stations in our dataset.</p><p>The authors of <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> propose an ontological model to represent metadata and data schema of meteorological observation data from the Météo-France archives. The focus of this work is to enable access and understanding of the data sources (weather reports) with adherence to FAIR principles, yet without actually transforming the observational data included in weather</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Un modèle sémantique en vue d&apos;améliorer la fairisation des données météorologiques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Amina</forename><surname>Annane</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mouna</forename><surname>Kamel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Nathalie</forename><surname>Aussenac-Gilles</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Cássia</forename><surname>Trojahn</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Comparot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Christophe</forename><surname>Baehr</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IC 2021 : 32es Journées francophones d&apos;Ingénierie des Connaissances (Proceedings of the 32nd French Knowledge Engineering Conference)</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxime</forename><surname>Lefrançois</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Bordeaux, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021-07-02">June 30 -July 2, 2021. 2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="29" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Transforming meteorological data into linked data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Auguste</forename><surname>Ghislain</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Óscar</forename><surname>Atemezing</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Corcho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jose</forename><surname>Garijo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">María</forename><surname>Mora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pablo</forename><surname>Poveda-Villalón</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Rozas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Boris</forename><surname>Vila-Suero</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Villazón-Terrazas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="290" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enabling the geospatial semantic web with parliament and GeoSPARQL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Robert</forename><surname>Battle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Kolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="370" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time ontology in OWL. W3C candidate recommendation 26 march 2020</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Chris</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">W3C Organism</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The modular SSN ontology: A joint W3C and OGC standard specifying the semantics of sensors, observations, sampling, and actuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Armin</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Krzysztof</forename><surname>Janowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxime</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Kerry</forename><surname>Lefrançois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Danh</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Joshua</forename><surname>Le Phuoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Raúl</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Rob</forename><surname>García-Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Claus</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SOSA: A lightweight ontology for sensors, observations, samples, and actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Krzysztof</forename><surname>Janowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Armin</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Simon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Danh</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maxime</forename><surname>Le Phuoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Lefrançois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Translation of relational and non-relational databases into RDF with xR2RML</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Loïc</forename><surname>Djimenou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron-Zucker</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Johan</forename><surname>Montagnat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">WEBIST 2015 -Proceedings of the 11th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Valérie</forename><surname>Monfort</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Karl-Heinz</forename><surname>Krempels</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Tim</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Majchrzak</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ziga</forename><surname>Turk</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lisbon, Portugal</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SciTePress</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015-05-22">20-22 May, 2015. 2015</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="443" to="454" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SAMOD: an agile methodology for the development of ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Silvio</forename><surname>Peroni</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">OWL: Experiences and Directions -Reasoner Evaluation</title>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mauro</forename><surname>Dragoni</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Maréa</forename><surname>Poveda-Villalón</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<editor>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ernesto</forename><surname>Jimenez-Ruiz</surname></persName>
		</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="55" to="69" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">QUDT quantities, units, dimensions and data types ontologies</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Hodges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ralph</forename><surname>Hodgson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Paul</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jack</forename><surname>Spivak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>NASA</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The RDF data cube vocabulary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dave</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Cyganiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-vocab-data-cube-20140116/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">W3C recommendation, W3C</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014-01">January 2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Weather data publication on the LOD using SOSA/SSN ontology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Roussey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stephan</forename><surname>Bernard</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Géraldine</forename><surname>André</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Daniel</forename><surname>Boffety</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="581" to="591" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Ontologies: Principles, methods and applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mike</forename><surname>Uschold</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Gruninger</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">The knowledge engineering review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="136" />
			<date type="published" when="1996">1996</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
