<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Metadatamatic: A Web application to Create a Dataset Description</title>
				<funder ref="#_QhWFFuf #_bQKr9PP #_G6k73T3 #_29fPjWw">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
							<email>olivier.corby@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Univ. Cote d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">I3S Sophia Antpolis</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Metadatamatic: A Web application to Create a Dataset Description</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">AE2A99541255B1830A03F3889992D202</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1145/3543873.3587328</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:53+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Information systems → Information integration</term>
					<term>Resource Description Framework (RDF)</term>
					<term>Web applications metadata, provenance, datasets, linked data, RDF, semantic web</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>This article introduces Metadatamatic, an open-source, online, userfriendly tool for generating the description of a knowledge base. It supports the description of any RDF dataset via a user-friendly web form that does not require prior knowledge of the vocabularies begin used, and can enrich the description with automatically generated statistics if the dataset is accessible from a public SPARQL endpoint. We discuss the models and methods behind the tool, and present some initial results suggesting that Metadatamatic can help in increasing the visibility of public knowledge bases.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>The deployment of semantic web technologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is driven by the desire, among others, to improve the findability, accessibility, interoperability, reusability, and reliability of data. In multiple domains, a growing number of knowledge bases (KBs) are made publicly available either through public SPARQL endpoints or downloadable RDF dumps. For instance, DBpedia is generated by turning information from Wikipedia pages into RDF.</p><p>To ensure the FAIR properties, KGs should provide rich metadata typically encompassing authors, licensing, provenance information, access interfaces, and a succinct overview of their content. There are several vocabularies available for writing such descriptions in RDF, with VoID <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, DCAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> and SPARQL-SD <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> being recommended by the W3C. However, during an experiment on a large number of publicly accessible KBs, we observed that less than 10% of them contain some form of provenance information <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, which is detrimental to their traceability and reusability.</p><p>In practice, the task of writing a KB description requires a solid understanding of multiple vocabularies in addition to VoID, DCAT, and SPARQL-SD, depending on the domain of interest. To alleviate this burden, this article presents a tool that supports the generation of a KG description without requiring prior knowledge of the vocabularies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">MOTIVATION</head><p>In a previous study <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, we attempted to retrieve the descriptions of 339 active KBs whose SPARQL endpoints were collected from public catalogues such as the LOD-Cloud, LinkedWiki and Wikidata. The results of this experimentation are represented graphically in KartoGraphi <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. These results revealed that only 33 out of 339 KBs contained any form of description. Among those with a description, 26 KBs contained information about their creators, contributors or publishers, 18 contained temporal information about their creation or publication, and 16 contained information about their licenses. We also attempted to retrieve the description hosted as .well-known/void files, as recommended in the VoID vocabulary, but found only 10 such files for the 339 KBs.</p><p>We attribute the lack of self-description in publicly available KBs to the lack of incentive and the difficulty of writing and maintaining these descriptions, starting with identifying which of the many vocabularies are appropriate. We assessed at least 11 vocabularies that are classically used for the general description of a KB (listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>), yet some authors found up to 32 possible vocabularies for that task <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. These vocabularies are both complementary and overlapping. More domain-specific vocabularies can also be used, such as the extension of DCAT for geographic datasets GeoDCAT <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Many articles have recommended "description profiles" in various use-cases and using various vocabularies, as shown in the survey by Benelli et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>While many parts of a description, such as statistics, can be extracted automatically, it remains necessary for KB providers to manually enter important parts of the description such as licensing and authoring information. Besides, identifying the appropriate classes and properties from the various vocabularies can be challenging. Initiatives such as DCAT-AP <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> or the COST Action for Distributed Knowledge Graphs have proposed lists of classes and properties for each description feature, but effectively writing the description remains a burdensome task.</p><p>The aim of Metadatamatic is to tackle the manual description challenge by providing a user-friendly method for creating a KB description via a web form, enriched with statistics automatically generated from the KB, and represented in RDF using the vocabularies recommended by the community.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">PRINCIPLES</head><p>Describing a KB is not a straightforward task, as several elements must be considered. For example, one must consider whether each named graph is a dataset of its own, or all the named graphs are part of the same dataset. One must also consider the level of detail required in the description, such as a precise description of each step of the process that generated the KB. To guide those decisions, we have studied existing vocabularies and proposals, and selected a KB description model that is as close as possible to the consensus that is currently emerging from the various initiatives. Moreover, the need for exhaustiveness can make the description process tedious, particularly in the case of large and complex KBs. To make the process simpler, a description tool must be able to extract as much information from the KB as possible. The following subsections explain how we support these principles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">A comprehensive description model</head><p>The survey <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> indicates that there are numerous vocabularies that can be used to represent the same features of a KB description. Using the results of our experiments with KartoGraphi <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, we studied the vocabularies used in the descriptions that we were able to gather, as well as the elements proposed in VoID, DCAT, DCAT-AP and DataID. From this study, we carefully selected 11 candidate vocabularies, listed in Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">1</ref>, that we could potentially used in the descriptions generated by Metadatamatic.</p><p>We retained three widely used and specialised vocabularies: VoID, DCAT, and SPARQL-SD, in addition to Dublin Core Terms for general properties such as the title and description of a KB. Other vocabularies were not used for various reasons. Some vocabularies are somehow restricted to specific communities, such as DataID. In our experiments, some well-known vocabularies like Schema.org and SKOS showed limited usage in this specific context of describing KBs. PROV-O and PAV are used to represent provenance information, yet different patterns are used to account for this information. As a consequence, a static web form would need to opt for a specific pattern and, arguably, would lack the flexibility required to be really helpful.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Automated description extraction</head><p>Metadatamatic converts the content of the web form into RDF, and utilises the previously proposed IndeGx framework <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> to extract KB descriptions from their content. We reused the SPARQL queries from this framework to extract various data from the content of the KB: list of vocabularies, language tags and named graphs, as well as the numbers of classes, properties and triples. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows the number of KBs that returned a result when IndeGx tried to retrieve the different description features from 339 endpoints. In particular, we can see that less than 15% of the endpoints managed to answer to the queries designed to extract the languages and the number of triples. This can be explained by the fact that those queries require to process respectively all the literals and all the triples of a KB, and therefore frequently time out.</p><p>Although some of these queries do not succeed, this automated extraction greatly reduces the effort for the user, particularly when dealing with KBs that contain a large number of named graphs and vocabularies. For example, the Scholarly Data base <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> contains more than thirty named graphs. Some features such as the KB license and languages have a limited set of most frequent values. To make the form more userfriendly, Metadatamatic suggests such frequent values with autocompletion. The values suggested for the license come from the RDFLicense dataset, while the values suggested for the languages come from the LexVo dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Description augmentation with aligned vocabularies</head><p>As mentioned above, multiple vocabularies can be used in a KB description and some of them have overlaps. Although using all available vocabularies simultaneously would make the description more tedious, in particular the part that is automatically generated, it would make the information more easily accessible and findable since users would not need to figure out which vocabularies were used. Therefore, for certain features, Metadatamatic can add equivalent triples using properties from other recognized vocabularies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">OPEN SOURCE AND ONLINE APPLICATION</head><p>Metadatamatic is accessible online 1 and its code is available on GitHub under the Apache 2.0 open source license. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref> shows the web interface and main sections of Metadatamatic. As can be seen, the form consists of multiple sections, each dedicated to a feature of the KB description: title, description, endpoint URL, etc. For each description feature, one or multiple values can be added depending on the feature, e.g. there can be multiple titles but only one publication date. The translation of each feature to RDF is displayed in Turtle beneath the feature, and the complete description is displayed at the bottom of the page and can be downloaded.</p><p>The user may also import a KB description which Metadatamatic uses to populate the form, thus making it possible to improve an existing description.</p><p>Let us now consider the example of the description of the French chapter of DBpedia. Metadatamatic offers the possibility to enter different titles and descriptions in different languages. They use respectively the dct:title and dct:description properties. Entering a SPARQL endpoint URL allows Metadatamatic to extract features directly from the endpoint. The endpoint is also added to the KB description with property void:sparqlEndpoint, and entails the creation of a resource of type dcat:DataService. In the license section, a list of suggestions is proposed by name and URI of well-known licenses. Upon selection, the URI of the license is entered as value of the dct:license property. The vocabularies, languages, triples, classes and properties features are extracted from the endpoint, they are respectively described using dct:language, void:triples, void:vocabulary, void:triples, void:classes, void:properties. The named graphs are also extracted atomatically and described using a data structure from SPARQL-SD. At  ¦ ¥</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">RESULTS</head><p>Since the launch of Metadatamatic on 12/08/2022, we started to collect descriptions of datasets that were not in the public catalogues, such as Wikidata, LinkedWiki, and the LOD-Cloud. Among them, the following datasets were never publicly described before: Listing 2: Extract of the description of the SemJoconde dataset, in Turtle format. § ¤ ex:dataset2 a dcat:Dataset, sd:Dataset; dct:title "SemJoconde"@en; dct:description "Representation semantique, basee sur CIDOC-CRM, de la base Joconde"@fr; dct:creator "Jean-Claude Moissinac"; dct:issued "2018-02-12"^^xsd:dateTime; dcat:keyword "artworks", "cultural heritage", "creators", "joconde database"; dct:language "fr", "en"; void:sparqlEndpoint semjoconde:query; </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSION</head><p>Metadatamatic was designed in the context of the DeKaLoG and D2KAB ANR projects. This service was motivated by the lack of dataset descriptions observed in the IndeGx framework experimentation and its visualization in the KartoGraphI website. We have shown how this open-source and online tool assists users in generating a description of their datasets without requiring prior knowledge of any vocabularies, and how it offers automated extraction and augmentation features to simplify the description process. We also showed that, as soon as it was released, this tool allowed us to make visible datasets that were unknown to major linked datasets indexes so far. Future works include the generation of FAIRness and accountability indicators to further improve the metadata available for linked open data sources.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Number of endpoints, out of a total of 339, for which IndeGx was able to process a given characteristic.</figDesc><graphic coords="3,317.96,83.69,252.20,158.32" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Listing 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>1 https://wimmics.github.io/voidmatic/ the time we did the extraction, the form yielded a description that consists of over 160 triples, whereas only 5 values were entered manually. The result of our description of the French chapter of DBpedia appears in Turtle as shown in Listing 1. Extract of the description of the French chapter of DBpedia, in Turtle format.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Example of Metadatamatic's web interface with a subset of the sections</figDesc><graphic coords="5,55.39,83.69,237.07,305.62" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>void:classes 23; void:properties 470; void:triples 16459098; void:vocabulary &lt;http://erlangen-crm.org/current/&gt;, &lt;http://datamusee.givingsense.eu/onto/&gt;; sd:namedGraph semjograph:dataid, semjograph:dmcreators. semjograph:dataid a sd:NamedGraph; sd:name semjograph:dataid. semjograph:dmcreators a sd:NamedGraph; sd:name semjograph:dmcreators.¦ ¥</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Vocabulary Short description</cell><cell cols="2">Vocabulary Short description</cell></row><row><cell>DCAT</cell><cell>Description of a catalog of KBs</cell><cell>Schema.org</cell><cell>General description</cell></row><row><cell>DCTerms</cell><cell>General description</cell><cell>SKOS</cell><cell>Concept description</cell></row><row><cell>DataID</cell><cell>Kb description, extends DCAT</cell><cell cols="2">SPARQL-SD Endpoint description</cell></row><row><cell>FOAF</cell><cell>Description of persons</cell><cell>VCard</cell><cell>People and organisations description</cell></row><row><cell>PAV</cell><cell>Provenance description, extends PROV-O</cell><cell>VoID</cell><cell>KB description</cell></row><row><cell>PROV-O</cell><cell>Provenance description</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note><p>show the properties and types used in the description intitially generated, and lists equivalent properties and types added once the use hits the Apply equivalences button.</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Most well-known vocabularies usable to describe a KB. The vocabularies in bold are those used in the description generated by Metadatamatic. Those is italic are those added after augmentation with aligned vocabularies.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Description feature Initial property or type Properties/types added after augmentation</cell></row><row><cell>Dataset rdf:type</cell><cell>dcat:Dataset</cell><cell>dcmitype:Dataset, void:Dataset, sd:Dataset, schema:Dataset, prov:Entity</cell></row><row><cell>Title</cell><cell>dct:title</cell><cell>schema:name</cell></row><row><cell>Description</cell><cell>dct:description</cell><cell>schema:description</cell></row><row><cell>Creator</cell><cell>dct:creator</cell><cell>prov:wasAttributedTo, pav:authoredBy, pav:createdBy</cell></row><row><cell>Publication date</cell><cell>dct:issued</cell><cell>schema:datePublished</cell></row><row><cell>Version</cell><cell>dcat:version</cell><cell>schema:version, dct:hasVersion, pav:version</cell></row><row><cell>Language</cell><cell>dct:language</cell><cell>schema:inLanguage</cell></row><row><cell>DataService rdf:type</cell><cell>dcat:DataService</cell><cell>sd:Service</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">DataService endpoint dcat:endpointURL</cell><cell>sd:endpoint</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Augmentation of the KB description with aligned vocabularies.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</head><p>This work is supported by the <rs type="projectName">ANR DeKaloG (Decentralized Knowledge Graphs)</rs> project, <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-19-CE23-0014</rs>, and by the <rs type="projectName">ANR D2KAB (Data to Knowledge in Agriculture and Biodiversity)</rs> project, <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-18-CE23-0017</rs>, both projects from <rs type="projectName">CE23 -Intelligence artificielle</rs> and by the <rs type="programName">3IA Côte d</rs>'<rs type="projectName">Azur</rs> <rs type="grantNumber">ANR-19-P3IA-0002</rs>.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_QhWFFuf">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-19-CE23-0014</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">ANR DeKaloG (Decentralized Knowledge Graphs)</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_bQKr9PP">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-18-CE23-0017</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">ANR D2KAB (Data to Knowledge in Agriculture and Biodiversity)</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_G6k73T3">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">CE23 -Intelligence artificielle</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">3IA Côte d</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_29fPjWw">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-19-P3IA-0002</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">Azur</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Semantic web for the working ontologist</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Dean</forename><surname>Allemang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">James</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Hendler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fabien</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<publisher>ACM Press</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RDF Dataset Profilinga Survey of Features, Methods, Vocabularies and Applications</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mohamed</forename><surname>Ben Ellefi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Zohra</forename><surname>Bellahsene</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">John</forename><surname>Breslin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Elena</forename><surname>Demidova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Stefan</forename><surname>Dietze</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Julian</forename><surname>Szymanski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Konstantin</forename><surname>Todorov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/SW-180294</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-180294" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">08</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Describing Linked Datasets with the VoID Vocabulary</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Richard</forename><surname>Cyganiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Hausenblas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Keith</forename><surname>Alexander</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/void/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">W3C Note. W3C</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">KartoGraphI: Drawing a Map of Linked Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pierre</forename><surname>Maillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fabien</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Extended Semantic Web Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">IndeGx: A Model and a Framework for Indexing RDF Knowledge Graphs with SPARQL-based Test Suits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Pierre</forename><surname>Maillot</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Fabien</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.websem.2023.100775</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.websem.2023.100775" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of Web Semantics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">100775</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2023-01">2023. Jan. 2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://joinup.ec.europa.eu/collection/semantic-interoperability-community-semic/solution/dcat-application-profile-data-portals-europe/release/211" />
		<title level="m">DCAT Application Profile for data portals in Europe</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Interoperable Europe Programme of the European Commission</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GeoDCAT-AP: Representing geographic metadata by using the &quot;DCAT application profile for data portals in Europe</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Perego</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Vlado</forename><surname>Cetl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anders</forename><surname>Friis-Christensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Michael</forename><surname>Lutz</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Joint UNECE/UNGGIM Europe Workshop on Integrating Geospatial and Statistical Standards</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Stockholm, Sweden</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gregory</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2013/REC-sparql11-service-description-20130321/" />
		<title level="m">SPARQL 1.1 Service Description. W3C Recommendation. W3C</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Peter</forename><surname>Winstanley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">David</forename><surname>Browning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Riccardo</forename><surname>Albertoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Alejandra</forename><forename type="middle">Gonzalez</forename><surname>Beltran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Simon</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Perego</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2020/REC-vocab-dcat-2-20200204/" />
		<title level="m">Data Catalog Vocabulary (DCAT) -Version 2. W3C Recommendation. W3C</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Entity Deduplication on ScholarlyData</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ziqi</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Andrea</forename><surname>Giovanni Nuzzolese</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><forename type="middle">Lisa</forename><surname>Gentile</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ESWC 2017</title>
		<title level="s">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<meeting>ESWC 2017</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
