<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multi-Level Visual Tours of Weather Linked Data</title>
				<funder ref="#_DaycPKG">
					<orgName type="full">Agence Nationale de la Recherche</orgName>
					<orgName type="abbreviated">ANR</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_JxAku86">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nadia</forename><surname>Yacoubi</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Damien</forename><surname>Graux</surname></persName>
							<email>damien.graux@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
							<email>catherine.faron@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>I3S</region>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multi-Level Visual Tours of Weather Linked Data</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">1613-0073</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">2E3E7E86BC2493D8FC01F4ACCF26BBF6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Weather data</term>
					<term>Spatio Temporal data</term>
					<term>Visualisation</term>
					<term>RDF Knowledge Graphs</term>
					<term>SPARQL endpoints Visualization and Interaction for Ontologies and Linked Data</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The recent trend of adopting linked-data principles to integrate and publish semantically described open data using W3C standards has led to a large amount of available resources. In particular, meteorological sensor data have been uplifted into public weather-focused RDF graphs, such as WeKG-MF which offers access to a large set of meteorological variables described through spatial and temporal dimensions. Nevertheless, these resources include huge numbers of raw observations that are tedious to explore by lay users. In this article, we aim at providing them with visual exploratory "tours", benefiting from RDF data cubes to present high-level aggregated views together with on-demand fine-grained details through a unified Web interface.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The recent trend of adopting linked-data principles to integrate and publish semantically described open data using W3C standards has led to a large amount of available resources. In particular, meteorological sensor data have been uplifted into public weather-focused RDF graphs, such as WeKG-MF graph which offers access to a huge number of sensor observations related to different weather variables, described through spatio-temporal dimensions. Hence, supporting lay users to browse, analyze, consume and reuse sensor data transformed and integrated into LOD datasets is challenging. In this article, we present the first release of a Web interface that enables users to visualize weather observational data at different levels of spatio-temporal granularity. We show how the WeKG-MF principles and the adoption of RDF data cubes can provide users with visual multi-level "tours". Our main objective is to provide users with interactive exploration means to navigate the WeKG-MF, leveraging RDF data cubes to present high-level aggregated views as well as fine details on demand through a unified Web interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The WeKG Spatio-Temporal Model</head><p>In this section, we present the WeKG spatio-temporal model and use-cases identified in the context of the D2KAB research project which highlighted the need to build a knowledge graph from historical records published as open data by the French weather service provider Météo-France. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">From weather Observations archives to an RDF Knowledge graph</head><p>In our previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, we have presented a self-contained semantic model that re-uses and extends standard ontologies, among which the GeoSPARQL ontology for spatial features and their relations <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>, the Time ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> for temporal entities, the Sensor, Observation, Sample, and Actuator (SOSA) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> and Semantic Sensor Network (SSN) ontologies <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> for sensors and observations, and the RDF Data Cube ontology <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> for aggregation and multidimensionality features. The WeKG model captures the semantics of atomic and fine-grained weather observations by reusing and extending SOSA classes as well as spatio-temporal time series of aggregate values using the RDF vocabulary of the data cube. The proposed model is generic enough to be adopted and extended by meteorological data providers to publish and integrate their sources while complying with Linked Data principles. Then, we built the WeKG-MF knowledge graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, based on this model, considering the open weather observations published by Météo-France<ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . The SPARQL WeKG-MF endpoint allows users to retrieve weather observations recorded every 3 hours by different sensors hosted by weather stations and related to different parameters (air temperature, humidity, wind speed, precipitation, atmospheric pressure, etc.). The Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarises some key statistics of WeKG-MF. WeKG-MF includes meteorological data from the period 2016-2021 and is continuously evolving to include new, newer and older data. The knowledge graph is intended to serve different use case scenarios in several domains, including agriculture, biodiversity and climate studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Use Case Scenarios for WeKG-MF</head><p>WeKG-MF was initially created to answer expert's needs in the context of the D2KAB French project <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> . A preliminary analysis revealed several competency questions that express the needs of experts to retrieve weather observations at different levels of granularity. For instance, an expert may be interested by the exact time of a day at which the minimum/maximum temperature was recorded and in this case, he is querying a fine-grained temporal entity represented by a xsd:dateTimeStamp literal in WeKG-MF. In several other situations, experts are more interested in aggregate values of some weather parameters, such as the daily total precipitation, the number of days with precipitation greater than 1 mm over a time period, or the monthly mean values of maximum, minimum and mean temperatures.</p><p>To address these needs, we reused the RDF Data Cube Vocabulary (DCV) <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> to create multidimensional RDF slices, that are pre-calculated by fixing temporal and spatial dimensions and by applying aggregation functions such as min/max/avg/sum on fine-grained observation. Thus,  a set of observations which applies to a spatio-temporal dimensions (e.g. a region, a weather station, a year, a time interval) is represented by the DCV class qb:Slice such as the attributes and measures attached to these observations are previously semantically described in a DCV qb:DataStructureDefinition class. This class enables to represent the slice's metadata along with the specification of dimensions, attributes, and measures. An example of a DSD definition of annual times series of min/max/avg air temperatures is available <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> .</p><p>We have experimented different strategies to generate the RDF materialized slices according to a given DSD. A first strategy consists in relying on a unique SPARQL query of the CONSTRUCT form, enabling to create homogeneous RDF slices that include only aggregate values of one unique weather parameter (e.g., air temperature). A second strategy consists in combining several SPARQL queries of the SELECT form, whose results sets are integrated into the same slice. As an example, Figure <ref type="figure">1</ref> illustrates the SPARQL query to calculate the total precipitation following the WMO documentation <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> which indicates that it is calculated for the day 𝑅 𝑑𝑎𝑦-𝑗 as the accumulated precipitation of a specific day 𝑗 from 6 𝑎𝑚 till 6 𝑎𝑚 of the following day 𝑗. Hence, six hours of the following UTC day shall be considered together with the current UTC day.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SPARQL-based Visual Tours</head><p>Aiming at simplifying the exploration of large RDF observational data available in WeKG-MF, we developed a Web application demo accessible at https://nadiaya2019.github.io/DemoKGViz/ using the D3 JavaScript library. The webpage provides different visualisations offering lay-users visual "tours" at different levels of granularity. Thanks to the WeKG spatio-temporal model and the incorporation of pre-calculated RDF slices, data retrieved from our SPARQL endpoint can be visualized with no additional transformations involved, while most approaches for Linked Data visualisation include pre-processing steps that can be time-consuming (see Section 4).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Retrieving Salient Information</head><p>In order to retrieve the WeKG-MF graph, we rely on three categories of SPARQL query patterns that could be easily adapted.</p><p>• An initial pattern allows to retrieve the Météo-France weather stations (and their geo-spatial coordinates) grouped by French regions. • The second pattern follows up, retrieves materialised RDF slices and collects values of at least one aggregate parameter pre-calculated for each station over a period of time. • The third pattern enables users to extract fine-grained, atomic observations based on results provided before. It provides detailed data giving information about aggregated value provenances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Visual Features</head><p>From a graphical point-of-view, we have developed several features to enrich the WeKG-MF users' experience. As illustrated in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>, we provide an interactive map allowing users to interact with the SPARQL endpoint by clicking on a French region (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>.a). This action leads to the execution of an initial SPARQL query like the one depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">2</ref> that retrieves weather stations and their corresponding timeseries of a specific parameter, e.g., air temperature during 3 years (2019-2021). Markers indicating geo-spatial locations of weather stations are added to the map and the timeseries are represented through two interactive line charts, which x-axis represents time and y-axis represents the daily average air temperatures, while the color encodes the different weather stations for the selected region. The first chart (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>.b -top-right) supports a brushing interaction allowing the user to select a time period to further explore the timeseries in the second chart (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>.c -middle-right), which x-axis is updated according to the time selection. The brush selection is represented by a gray rectangle that can be resized at any time to expand/reduce the time span and by consequence update the view of the middle chart. Moreover, the brush selection can be handled through a click-and-drag movement to modify the time period while keeping the same time span. This chart (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>.c -middle-right) supports interaction through a hovering technique, which displays a tooltip with detailed information on the temperatures of a specific weather station and at the same time a third chart appears (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">3</ref>.d -bottom-right). Indeed, this chart offers a fine-grained view on WeKG-KG observations by displaying for a specific date 𝑑𝑎𝑦-𝑗 un-aggregated atomic observations including those of the previous and following days. It supports also interaction through a hovering technique which displays a vertical line that the user could move to visualize values at the specific time of the day. Therefore, through this view, a user may easily explore the WeKG-MF knowledge graph from high-level aggregated timeseries to the elements from where the timeseries were calculated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Related Work</head><p>Several research projects have focused on providing visualisation and exploration tools for LD datasets. Indeed, exploring, browsing and querying these datasets through space and time is very relevant for users but not straightforward for developers in order to transform RDF data into meaningful visualizations that suit users' needs. For an extensive review on LD exploration and visualization tools, we refer interested readers to <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. While most existing approaches focus on how to shift pipelines to import/map/transform RDF data into data suitable for visualisations <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11]</ref>, few of them highlight the importance of RDF modeling to easily support the generation of meaningful visualisations. Indeed, research works such as CubeViz <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> or OpenCube <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> aim to provide users with data cubes visualization and interactive analysis tools. However, to the best of our knowledge, multi-visualisation interfaces that combine high-level views on aggregated data using the RDF data cube vocabulary <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and fine-grained views of un-aggregated values do not exist.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Conclusion and Future Works</head><p>We presented the first release of a Web application that offers interactive multi-level tours based on high-level aggregated views together with on-demand fine-grained data, and this through a unified multi-visualisations interface. In near future, we aim to work on a user evaluation study of our system to provide advanced analysis functionalities enabling experts to compare climatic conditions across geospatial and temporal dimensions. Moreover, we plan to enrich the interface to track data quality issues such as missing values across timeseries of weather parameters.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Query to retrieve avg. daily temp. timeseries computed from the observation in WeKG-MF recorded by weather stations located in "Nouvelle Aquitaine" French region.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3: WeKG-MF exploration and navigation interface.</figDesc><graphic coords="6,109.13,84.20,375.01,270.47" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Key Statistics of the WeKG-MF Knowledge Graph.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">SPARQL endpoint → https://weakg.i3s.unice.fr/sparql</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of RDF Triples</cell><cell>123.413.015 Weather stations</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell>Total Observations</cell><cell>16.433.031 Weather properties</cell><cell>22</cell></row><row><cell>Observations per weather property</cell><cell>≈ 416.762 Meteorological features</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Links to Wikidata</cell><cell>92</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://www.meteofrance.com/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>http://www.d2kab.org</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://github.com/Wimmics/weather-kg/blob/main/meteo/dataset-metadata/DSD-Definition.ttl</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgements. This study was carried out within the <rs type="projectName">D2KAB</rs> project "<rs type="projectName">From Data to Knowledge in Agronomy and Biodiversity</rs>", financed by the <rs type="funder">French National Research Agency</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">ANR-18-CE23-0017</rs>). We are also grateful to <rs type="person">Aline Menin</rs> and <rs type="person">Olivier Corby</rs> for their valuable help.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_JxAku86">
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">D2KAB</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_DaycPKG">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-18-CE23-0017</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">From Data to Knowledge in Agronomy and Biodiversity</orgName>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A model for meteorological knowledge graphs: Application to Météo-France observational data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yacoubi Ayadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>ICWE</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enabling the geospatial semantic web with parliament and geosparql</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Battle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Kolas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="355" to="370" />
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Time ontology in OWL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Little</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/owl-time/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SOSA: A lightweight ontology for sensors, observations, samples, and actuators</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Janowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Phuoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lefrançois</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="10" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The modular SSN ontology: A joint W3C and OGC standard specifying the semantics of sensors, observations, sampling, and actuation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Haller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Janowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">J D</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lefrançois</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Taylor</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Phuoc</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lieberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>García-Castro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Atkinson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="32" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The RDF Data Cube Vocabulary, W3C Recommendation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Reynolds</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cyganiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-vocab-data-cube-20140116/" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<pubPlace>W3C</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A knowledge graph of observational weather data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Yacoubi Ayadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Wekg-Mf</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ESWC 2022 Satellite Events</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://library.wmo.int/doc_num.php?explnum_id=9253" />
		<title level="m">Handbook on climat and climat temp reporting</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>World Meteorological Organization</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Po</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Bikakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Desimoni</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Linked Data Visualization Tools</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="72" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">From linked data querying to visual search: Towards a visualization pipeline for LOD exploration</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Menin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faron</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Corby</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Freitas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Gandon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Winckler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies</title>
		<meeting>the 17th International Conference on Web Information Systems and Technologies</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">VizKG: A framework for visualizing SPARQL query results over knowledge graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Raissya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Darari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Ekaputra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<publisher>CEUR-WS</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3023</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="102" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Abicht</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Stadler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Auer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A.-C</forename><surname>Ngonga Ngomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Soru</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">CubeVizexploration and visualization of statistical linked data</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>WWW</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploiting linked data cubes with opencube toolkit</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Kalampokis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nikolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Haase</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Cyganiak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Stasiewicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Karamanou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zotou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zeginis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Tambouris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Tarabanis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ISWC Poster &amp; Demonstration</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
