<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Interactive multimedia</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Maroua</forename><surname>Tikat</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marco</forename><surname>Winckler</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michel</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Interactive multimedia</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">09184F2A8E4FA183B954079D0CDD02B3</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 11 Nov 2021</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>music dataset</term>
					<term>multimedia data</term>
					<term>visualization techniques</term>
					<term>data quality</term>
					<term>multivariate data</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>published or not. The documents may come from teaching and research institutions in France or abroad, or from public or private research centers. L'archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est destinée au dépôt et à la diffusion de documents scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Interactive multimedia visualization for exploring and fixing a multi-dimensional metadata base of popular musics</head><p>Maroua Tikat, Marco Winckler, and Michel Buffa University Côte d'Azur, SPARKS/wimmics team, Inria, CNRS, I3S, France [maroua.tikat, winckler, michel.buffa]@univ-cotedazur.fr</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>This position paper presents our findings and ideas raised whilst creating a knowledge graph for music datasets. Working on a knowledge graph makes it possible to interlink resources with rich semantic relationships, which helps increase knowledge. If we take for example a music dataset, it would offer a large scope of metadata describing music, including multimedia dimensions that count textual (e.g. title, lyrics), graphical (e.g. curves), and audio (e.g., the sound produced), as well as metadata qualifying the works (e.g., date and time of recording, authors, performers...) and uses (e.g. song covers, classification for a specific use,...). All these resources are given URIs that can be referenced to documents describing them and can be shared across datasets. In order to explore music datasets, we have proposed in a previous work <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> the use of information visualization techniques. Nonetheless, during the visualization process we found some patterns that suggest inconsistencies in the dataset. As a matter of fact, the related work section shows that all the music datasets containing a large volume of data have been built from several data sources, either from public sources on the web, or from audio analysis or lyrics analysis, which will inevitably generate data incoherence. These observations led us to consider a new perspective for using information visualization techniques as a tool for assessing data quality, comparing the results of fixing methods and communicating data inconsistencies to the user. In the rest of this position paper we discuss the underlying background for characterizing the problem, especially on the field of music datasets, and we envisage a method aimed at helping to fix data quality problems.</p><p>2 Background and related work</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Music datasets</head><p>Musical contents can be described in many multimedia dimensions (ex. lyrics, chords, sounds, metadata...). Nonetheless, most of music datasets are specialized on a few types of attributes or on a specific musical genre. In order to have a more complete description of songs, some new datasets have been created by aggregating multiple data sources:</p><p>-The WASABI dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>: available at https://github.com/micbuffa/WasabiDataset, it contains over 2 MM commercial songs issued from multiple sources. It features a rich set of cultural metadata on songs, albums and artists, and also contains metadata extracted from NLP analysis of lyrics and MIR (Music Information Retrieval) analysis of song audio contents. An Ontology describing the WASABI dataset is also publicly available <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . -The Million Song Dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>: this one includes over 1 MM contemporary popular songs, with metadata extracted mainly from audio content analysis and lyric-related metadata in the form of "bag of words". -MusicBrainz: a free online music database, available under an open licence, which collects music metadata (ex. artits, albums, labels, etc) and makes it available to the public. There is no information about lyrics but a companion web site (i.e. Acous-ticBrainz) offers MIR audio analysis of a subset of the songs (crowd sourced). -MusicWeb <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and its latest version MusicLynx <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>: allow the exploration of a graph of artist similarities, built by linking several free public data sources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Visualization techniques used in the musical field</head><p>Music datasets are often huge, containing hundreds of thousands, or millions of songs.</p><p>In this context, information visualization techniques might be a suitable alternative for exploring music contents, identify patterns, trends, and correlations. According to a recent survey done on visualizations for music related data <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>, musical collections techniques such as glyph, some of which cannot be grouped explicitly. Musicians are viewed most often through graphs and timelines, while 3D rendering is used for instruments. Charts can be used for all data types listed. Sunbursts, Node-Link Trees, Bubble Charts and Treemaps are used to explore music rankings using interactive visualization <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>. They all allow to represent music data content (artist's name, tracks' position,...) and music genre. As far as audio analysis is concerned, several approaches have been considered to determine the structure of a song <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> [11] and classify them (intro, theme, verse, chorus, solo and outro) based on different musical dimensions such as melody, harmony, rhythm, and timbre. We cite the following visualization techniques: recurrence plots, arc diagrams, chroma features and rythmograms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Types of data quality defects found using visualizations</head><p>Whilst inconsistencies are not frequent in the WASABI dataset, we were able to spot some of them during the exploration process using a visualization tool called MGExplorer. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> illustrates an example of duplicated entry for artists found during the exploration process. Hereafter we present a short list of the types of data quality defects we have found. We classify the problems in two categories, as follows:</p><p>1) Intrinsic defects encompass cases of duplicated data, missing data, disambiguation of artists with similar names, wrong formats for dates, conflicts between values of the same property collected from different data sources, broken links, etc.</p><p>2) Scenario problems related are specific to the application domain, such as: i) the same song with more than one producer or performer, according to the source; ii) a big difference between the number of songs produced in one single year, compared to others years (is it normal -related to some real life events? Is it an error during data collection?); iii ) songs classified in multiples genres, which might be the expression of errors in the classification of divergence of opinions among how songs could be classified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Methods to assess data quality, to complete and to fix the dataset</head><p>Some of the methods we found in the literature allows both the detection and the correction of dataset inconsistencies, as follows:</p><p>-Sourcing knowledge <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>: a solution that takes advantage of the development of the web and online communities to help fill blanks in a dataset. It can also be used to detect and fix outliers in a dataset. -Support Vector Machines <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> and matrix factorization: methods that have been used to predict entities' types. association rule mining <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> and neural network : can be used to predict relations based on chains of other relations, -Retrospective evaluation: an approach that allows people to assess a value by saying whether it is true or false. -Reasoning: inference techniques are highly used in the semantic web community to check for errors in knowledge graphs, by adding rules and restrictions on the ontology, provided that the latter is rich. -Interquartile range and kernel density estimation: these methods are used to correct numerical outliers in a dataset. -DeFacto <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>: one of the few methods to correct a dataset, it assigns confidence scores to statements, based on their occurences in different web pages. -Fact validation through consensus measurement <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>: an automatic approach using knowledge graph interlinks to detect erroneous numerical values. It exploits the links between identical resources and apply different matching functions between the properties of individual sources. Facts in a knowledge graph are assumed to be wrong if several other sources have a consensus for a contradictory fact. -Graph embedding TransE <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>: a method that allows link prediction on large databases by interpreting relationships as translations operating on the low-dimensional embeddings of the entities.</p><p>Whilst several methods for detecting problems with data quality exist, our research questions are focused on how to communicate these problems to the users. For example, it is a duplicated record and not a homonyms artists. In the example given by Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, the disambiguation can be made by allowing users to explore other attributes associated to the artists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Our approach</head><p>As we shall see, detecting and solving data quality problems might require a decisionmaking processing involving users. For example, different algorithms might provide divergent analysis for music genre and the correct classification will depend on the users' needs. For that, we propose to put users in the loop for detecting data quality problems and for deciding how the problems must be solved. Moreover, rather than propose completion/repairing methods (e.g., link prediction, duplication detection, missing URL, etc.), our approach allows users to apply existing methods and visualize the outcomes in terms of repairs proposed; ultimately users should be able to check if the corrections Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>: Methodology fulfill their needs (or not). Figure <ref type="figure">2</ref> presents a view at glance of our approach for detecting and solving quality problems whilst exploring music dataset using visualization techniques. Our approach encompasses the following premises:</p><p>-Allow continuous integration of data from several sources, including results of audio and song lyrics analysis; In addition to standard music data, we will be adding emotion analysis, structure detection (verse, chorus, etc.), topic analysis, etc.; -Use information visualization techniques for multivariate data (such as MGExplorer and Parallel Coordinates) to represent all sort of data; -Identify the problems with data quality during the exploration process using visualization techniques; Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> shows an example of a problem detected in the WASABI dataset using MGExplorer, which is a duplicate artist. -Solutions for detecting problems can be: manual, automatic or both; -Visualization techniques can accommodate the results of data correction adding an explanation to the context of use; -Compare the results of methods for detecting problems, allowing the users to decide about the outcomes of the corrections proposed. Validation of data correction/completion can be done quantitatively, by running against some measures (i.e number of missing properties, number of artists that require disambiguation) or qualitatively (i.e present a before/after visualization, and do user testing with real users to evaluate the refined data compared to what we had previously and evaluate the tools themselves).</p><p>This paper presented a preliminary work towards the visualization of music datasets. It includes a discussion about problems and potential solutions for integration methods for fixing data quality problems along the visualization process. As we have discussed, these data quality problems arose by continuous data integration (ex. new songs, new analysis of old songs, conflicts detected over time...). So that, we claim that data quality of music datasets is part of a continuous curation process rather than a definite state of the dataset. For that, we propose a methodology aiming at visualizing music datasets, highlighting problems found during the exploration process, as well as allowing to compare solutions to fix those problems. The next steps should be to deal with integration of corrective methods for fixing problems and support the versioning of data (a main requirement for comparison of the methods' outcomes). For this purpose, MGExplorer will be used as a proof of concept to illustrate the feasibility of the methodology proposed. We are currently working on running prototype that could be used to test our hypothesis with end users. Finally, despite the fact that our work is focused on the music dataset WABASI, we suggest that the solution might be suitable to other types of datasets to be explored in the future.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1: Visualization of artists by their MusicBrainz id</figDesc><graphic coords="4,134.77,116.83,345.83,99.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,134.77,116.83,345.82,247.84" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>https://github.com/micbuffa/WasabiDataset/blob/master/ontology/wsb-1.0.ttl</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crowdsourcing linked data quality assessment</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Acosta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International semantic web conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="260" to="276" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Musicweb: an open linked semantic platform for music metadata</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Allik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Mora-Mcginity</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Fazekas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sandler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 15th International Semantic Web Conf</title>
		<meeting>15th International Semantic Web Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Musiclynx: Exploring music through artist similarity graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Allik</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Thalmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Sandler</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Companion Proceedings of the The Web Conference</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Translating embeddings for modeling multi-relational data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Antoine</forename><surname>Bordes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2787" to="2795" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The million song dataset</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">"</forename><surname>Bertin-Mahieux</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="596" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The wasabi dataset: cultural, lyrics and audio analysis metadata about 2 million popular commercially released songs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Algorithms for association rule mining -a general survey and comparison</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jochen</forename><surname>Hipp</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Nakhaeizadeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM SIGKDD Explorations Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey on visualizations for musical data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Khulusi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kusnick</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Meinecke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Computer Graphics Forum</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="110" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Exploring music rankings with interactive visualization leandro</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Leandro Guedes</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Symposium on Applied Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Symposium on Applied Computing</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="214" to="219" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Defacto -deep fact validation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lehmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International semantic web conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin, Heidelberg</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="312" to="327" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Audio-based music structure analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Paulus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Müller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Klapuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. of the 11th International Society for Music Information Retrieval Conf</title>
		<meeting>of the 11th International Society for Music Information Retrieval Conf</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="625" to="636" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards linked data fact validation through measuring consensus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Shuangyan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Mathieu D'aquin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CEUR Workshop Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Type prediction for efficient coreference resolution in heterogeneous semantic graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sleeman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Finin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IEEE 7th International Conference on Semantic Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="85" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Audio-based music visualization for music structure analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Bello</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 7th Sound and Music Computing Conference</title>
		<meeting>the 7th Sound and Music Computing Conference</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
