<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The Need for Better RDF Archiving Benchmarks</title>
				<funder ref="#_wCZQ9JV">
					<orgName type="full">Research Foundation -Flanders (FWO)</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_eC64FTy">
					<orgName type="full">Independent Research Fund Denmark (DFF)</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">Poul Due Jensen Foundation</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder ref="#_PJ82NTh">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Pelgrin</surname></persName>
							<email>olivier@cs.aau.dk</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Aalborg University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ruben</forename><surname>Taelman</surname></persName>
							<email>ruben.taelman@ugent.be</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Ghent University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="BE">Belgium</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Luis</forename><surname>Galárraga</surname></persName>
							<email>luis.galarraga@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">INRIA</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Katja</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
							<email>katja.hose@tuwien.ac.at</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Aalborg University</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="DK">Denmark</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="institution">TU Wien</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="AT">Austria</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The Need for Better RDF Archiving Benchmarks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">1613-0073</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">24FE3D6BDDD0A060D718D0AE9F40DF44</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The advancements and popularity of Semantic Web technologies in the last decades have led to an exponential adoption and availability of Web-accessible datasets. While most solutions consider such datasets to be static, they often evolve over time. Hence, efficient archiving solutions are needed to meet the users' and maintainers' needs. While some solutions to these challenges already exist, standardized benchmarks are needed to systematically test the different capabilities of existing solutions and identify their limitations. Unfortunately, the development of new benchmarks has not kept pace with the evolution of RDF archiving systems. In this paper, we therefore identify the current state of the art in RDF archiving benchmarks and discuss to what degree such benchmarks reflect the current needs of real-world use cases and their requirements. Through this empirical assessment, we highlight the need for the development of more advanced and comprehensive benchmarks that align with the evolving landscape of RDF archiving.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>The continuous advancement and widespread adoption of Semantic Web technologies have generated a growing demand for robust systems to manage knowledge graphs. This demand is particularly pronounced for RDF, the Semantic Web's most prevalent and accessible data model. Along with the rest of the Web, Semantic Web data is continuously evolving <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">3]</ref>. This has inspired related work on capturing metadata, such as RDF-star <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref>, and in general raised the need to keep track of the revision history of those datasets for the sake of multiple applications. Examples are version control or historical data analytics, which, in turn, have sparked the development of dedicated techniques and systems for RDF archiving <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>.</p><p>The availability of widely adopted benchmarks is of crucial importance for the development of RDF archiving systems. Standardized benchmarks enable the impartial evaluation of new indexing and storage techniques, as well as the performance of query engines. Although numerous benchmarks have been designed specifically for evaluating RDF stores <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>, the number of benchmarking options for RDF archiving systems remains limited <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>In this paper, we present an analysis of the current state of RDF archiving benchmarks through an evaluation of their strengths and limitations. We show that despite advancements in the field, current benchmarks do not sufficiently capture emerging challenges faced by archiving systems. We use this finding to derive a set of requirements, that we believe, are essential for benchmarks to advance research and development of RDF archives.</p><p>The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. First, we discuss the current state of RDF archiving research and relevant benchmarks in Section 2. Second, in Section 3, we discuss the shortcomings of current RDF archiving benchmarks and our recommendations and requirements for the future. Finally, Section 4 concludes the paper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Related Work</head><p>We now provide a brief survey of the available RDF archiving systems as well as of existing languages and SPARQL extensions designed for RDF archives. Furthermore, this section delves into existing benchmarks tailored for assessing the performance of RDF archiving systems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">RDF Archiving</head><p>RDF archiving, at its core, consists of storing and querying the entire evolution history of an RDF graph. This has proven to be a challenging task due to the additional temporal dimension compared to traditional RDF stores. While the design of efficient indexing and querying systems for RDF archives is still an ongoing effort, multiple approaches have been proposed throughout the years <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Existing works can generally be categorized into three main paradigms <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, Independent Copies (IC), Change-based (CB), and Timestamp-based (TB), with some modern approaches proposing the use of a combination of those <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">13]</ref>. Some approaches are now able to scale to much larger RDF archives compared to early proposals <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>, however querying capabilities remain limited. Efficient processing of complex archive queries is one of the key areas of development for the future.</p><p>In contrast to conventional RDF, the existence of multiple versions within an RDF archive introduces the need for novel query types that can be hardly expressed in standard SPARQL. Some approaches propose the extension of SPARQL to support temporal queries, i.e., by specifying a timestamp or interval in which the query results should hold <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Other works attempt to formally categorize the different possible types of queries on RDF archives <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref>, but do not address the implementation of these categorizations via formal SPARQL extensions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Benchmarks for RDF Archives</head><p>Benchmarks play a crucial role in guiding the development of systems by facilitating their evaluation and enabling comparisons with existing systems in terms of implementation and design. Due to being a relatively new area in RDF data management, we only account for three benchmarks tailored for RDF archiving in the literature: EvoGen <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>, BEAR <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, and SPBv <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>EvoGen <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> is a benchmark based on the LUBM <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> data generator extended to support evolving RDF scenarios. The benchmark data can be configured on the desired number of versions and the magnitude of changes. The querying workload is derived from the 14 LUBM queries and includes variations of materialization, delta, and mixed queries. Due to the nature of the LUBM queries, support for RDFS reasoning is needed to resolve the complete result sets.</p><p>BEAR <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is a benchmark for RDF archives consisting of three different RDF archives. Those different flavours, namely BEAR-A, BEAR-B and BEAR-C, are extracted from real-world datasets, and are characterised by their various sizes and change behaviour. BEAR comes with predefined query workloads, based on single triple pattern queries for both BEAR-A and BEAR-B, while for BEAR-C, a set of 10 full SPARQL queries are proposed.</p><p>SPBv <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> is a benchmark for RDF archives that consists of a data generator based on the Semantic Publishing Benchmark (SPB) <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> from the Linked Data Benchmark Council (LDBC) <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. The number of versions and the size of the data can be configured, as well as the number of generated queries. The generated data comes as full versions, changesets, or both. The query workload consists of SPARQL queries where versions are represented as named graphs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Benchmarking RDF Archives</head><p>In this section, we examine the qualities and features that a benchmark for RDF archiving should strive to possess. We propose that benchmarks for RDF Archives should strive for three main overarching qualities, namely reproducibility, realism, and configurability. Reproducibility represents the ease at which the benchmark results can be shared and reproduced by others. Realism is about how the benchmark setting, both in the choice of dataset and query loads, models or emulates the real world. Configurability represents the ability of the benchmark to propose workloads of various sizes, relevant for a wide range of system configurations and use cases. We further detail our recommendations of a concrete implementation of the aforementioned qualities by first detailing the choice of data. We then will discuss the design of query workloads, and finally, we discuss whether existing benchmarks fulfill those requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Dataset</head><p>The choice of data is an important aspect when designing a benchmark. Current benchmarks use either a configurable generator for synthetic data <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b14">15]</ref>, or directly provide data based on existing real world datasets <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. As discussed by Duan et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>, many data generators produce data that is not necessarily representative of real-world RDF datasets. However, they also demonstrate the possibility to make generators truer to the real world by taking into account their proposed coherence metric in the generation process. We are although not aware of any other generator-based benchmark for RDF archiving taking advantage of this metric.</p><p>Most importantly, a benchmark should cover different, realistic, scaling options. In the RDF archiving world, the scaling options do not only cover different data sizes, but also the history's size, i.e. the number of versions and the magnitude of changes within each version. Generator-based benchmarks should provide users with all the necessary scaling parameters, while real-world-based benchmarks should offer different datasets scaling along those axes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Query Workload</head><p>Early RDF archiving systems could be adequately tested with single triple pattern queries, but contemporary archiving benchmarks should prioritize comprehensive SPARQL query workloads. We believe that efficient support for full SPARQL represents a major challenge that RDF archiving systems currently need to solve. Consequently, in order to fulfill our realism requirement, benchmarks should provide comprehensive assessment of those capabilities, guiding the development of existing and new systems. Benchmark query workloads should be carefully designed to align with real-world use cases. Following recommendations from the LDBC <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>, a "choke-point" approach to the design of the benchmark should be considered through a comprehensive evaluation of real-world RDF archive usages.</p><p>Finally, the lack of an accepted standard to formulate archiving queries into SPARQL is a major brake for the design of benchmark queries. Addressing this issue necessitates a dedicated standardization effort, drawing inspiration from the RDF stream community, and the RSP-QL standardization <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. This would require a broader study of the overlap between RDF stream processing and RDF archiving, notably on the relation between temporal graphs and archives. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dataset</head><p>Reproducibility Realism (data) Realism (queries) Configurability</p><p>EvoGen <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> Synthetic -/+ -+ + BEAR <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> Real-world + + --SPBv <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> Synthetic -/+ -+ +</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Comparison of Existing RDF Archiving Benchmarks</head><p>Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_0">1</ref> summarizes the characteristics of the existing RDF archiving benchmarks. Among the available benchmarks, two of them rely on synthetic data generated through a data generator.</p><p>Generator-based systems fulfill the configurability criteria easily due to their nature, but may fall short of also proving their realism, while their reproducibility is dependent on the sharing of the exact parameters and random seed. Both EvoGen <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref> and SPBv <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> provide SPARQL queries of varied nature, but only focus on the generation of one restrictive type of datasets, which have not been evaluated realism, e.g., via the coherence metric <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref>. BEAR <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> on the other hand provides datasets of various sizes, based on real-world data. This increases the reproducibility and relevance of the benchmark compared to generator-based ones. The number of scalability options is however limited, but BEAR still offers five different alternative datasets. However, 10 full SPARQL queries are only provided for one of the datasets, the others being limited to single triple pattern queries. As discussed in Section 3.2, this limits BEAR's realism, and makes the evaluation of SPARQL-capable archiving systems quite limited.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Conclusion</head><p>In this paper, we presented the current state in RDF archiving systems and benchmarks. We have proposed a set of requirements that benchmarks should have in order to contribute to the advancement of the field. We showed that among the only three available benchmarks for RDF archiving systems, none of them proposes a satisfactory set of features. This ranges from a general lack of realism w.r.t. the real world, lack of SPARQL support, or concerns with reproducibility. We see several areas open for future work. First, precisely defining the semantics and syntax of SPARQL archive queries would benefit greatly to the wider RDF community. This would open the door for standardized support across various RDF stores and research systems. Secondly, benchmarks relevant to the modern challenges faced by RDF archiving applications and systems are needed to guide and evaluate efforts in that area. We believe that this is paramount to current development efforts of fully-fledged RDF archiving systems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Comparison table of existing RDF Archiving benchmarks.</figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgments</head><p>This research is partially funded by the <rs type="funder">Poul Due Jensen Foundation</rs> and the <rs type="funder">Independent Research Fund Denmark (DFF)</rs> under grant agreement no. <rs type="grantNumber">DFF-8048-00051B</rs>, the <rs type="projectName">TAILOR Network</rs> (<rs type="programName">EU Horizon 2020 research and innovation program</rs> under <rs type="grantNumber">GA 952215</rs>), and the <rs type="funder">Research Foundation -Flanders (FWO)</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">1274521N</rs>).</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_eC64FTy">
					<idno type="grant-number">DFF-8048-00051B</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">TAILOR Network</orgName>
					<orgName type="program" subtype="full">EU Horizon 2020 research and innovation program</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_wCZQ9JV">
					<idno type="grant-number">GA 952215</idno>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_PJ82NTh">
					<idno type="grant-number">1274521N</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Evaluating query and storage strategies for RDF archives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Fernández</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Umbrich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Polleres</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Knuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="247" to="291" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge Graph (R)Evolution and the Web of Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MEPDaW@ISWC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="7" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Towards fully-fledged archiving for RDF datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pelgrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Galárraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="903" to="925" />
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Foundations of RDF* and SPARQL* (An Alternative Approach to Statement-Level Metadata in RDF)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Hartig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
			<publisher>AMW</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">StarBench: Benchmarking RDF-star Triplestores</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Abuoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aebeloe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dell'aglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Keen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">QuWeDa@ISWC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Apples and oranges: a comparison of RDF benchmarks and real RDF datasets</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kementsietsidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Srinivas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Udrea</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<publisher>SIGMOD</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="145" to="156" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The linked data benchmark council project</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Boncz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fundulaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gubichev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Larriba-Pey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Neumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Datenbank-Spektrum</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">13</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="129" />
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">LUBM: A benchmark for OWL knowledge base systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Pan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Heflin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="158" to="182" />
			<date type="published" when="2005">2005</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spbv: Benchmarking linked data archiving systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Papakonstantinou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Flouris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fundulaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Stefanidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Roussakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">BLINK@ISWC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1932">1932. 2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Scaling Large RDF Archives To Very Long Histories</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pelgrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Taelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Galárraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>ICSC</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="41" to="48" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Triple Storage for Random-Access Versioned Querying of RDF Archives</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Taelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vander Sande</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Van Herwegen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Mannens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Verborgh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Decentralized collaborative knowledge management using git</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Arndt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Naumann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Radtke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Martin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Marx</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Web Semant</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">54</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="29" to="47" />
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">GLENDA: Querying RDF Archives with full SPARQL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Pelgrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Taelman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Galárraga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
			<publisher>ESWC</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">T-SPARQL: A tsql2-like temporal query language for RDF</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Grandi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ADBIS</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010">2010</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="21" to="30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The EvoGen Benchmark Suite for Evolving RDF Data</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Meimaris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Papastefanatos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">MEPDaW@ESWC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="35" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Benchmarking RDF query engines: The LDBC semantic publishing benchmark</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kotsev</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Minadakis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Papakonstantinou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Erling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Fundulaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kiryakov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">BLINK@ISWC</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">RSP-QL semantics: A unifying query model to explain heterogeneity of RDF stream processing systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dell'aglio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Valle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Calbimonte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ó</forename><surname>Corcho</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Int. J. Semantic Web Inf. Syst</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="44" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
