<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="fr">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Assisting Biologists in Editing Taxonomic Information by Confronting Multiple Data Sources using Linked Data Standards</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-06-26">26 Jun 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
							<email>franck.michel@cnrs.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sandrine</forename><surname>Tercerie</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonia</forename><surname>Ettorre</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Olivier</forename><surname>Gargominy</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><forename type="middle">Faron</forename><surname>Zucker</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Catherine</forename><surname>Faron-Zucker</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Gargominy</forename><surname>Olivier</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>I3S</addrLine>
									<settlement>Sophia-Antipolis</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Muséum national d&apos;Histoire naturelle</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Paris</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Assisting Biologists in Editing Taxonomic Information by Confronting Multiple Data Sources using Linked Data Standards</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-06-26">26 Jun 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D4C8B14711F0A610EAD10A72A274DEA2</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3897/biss.3.37421</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 28 Jun 2019 Received: 17 Jun 2019 |</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:54+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Web API</term>
					<term>data integration</term>
					<term>Linked Data</term>
					<term>SPARQL</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="fr">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>and fungus <ref type="bibr">(Gargominy et al. 2018)</ref>. TAXREF registers all species recorded in metropolitan France and overseas territories, accounting for 260,000+ biological taxa (200,000+ species) along with 570,000+ scientific names. The TAXREF-Web application compares data available in TAXREF with corresponding data from third-party data sources, points out disagreements and allows biologists to add, remove or amend TAXREF accordingly. This requires that TAXREF-Web developers write a specific piece of code for each considered Web API to align TAXREF representation with the Web API counterpart. This task is timeconsuming and makes maintenance of the web application cumbersome.</p><p>In this presentation, we report on a new implementation of TAXREF-Web that harnesses the Linked Data standards: Resource Description Framework (RDF), the Semantic Web format to represent knowledge graphs, and SPARQL, the W3C standard to query RDF graphs. In addition, we leverage the SPARQL Micro-Service architecture <ref type="bibr">(Michel et al. 2018)</ref>, a lightweight approach to query Web APIs using SPARQL. A SPARQL micro-service is a SPARQL endpoint that wraps a Web API service; it typically produces a small, resource-centric RDF graph by invoking the Web API and transforming the response into RDF triples.</p><p>We developed SPARQL micro-services to wrap the Web APIs of GBIF, World Register of Marine Species (WoRMS), FishBase, Index Fungorum, Pan-European Species directories Infrastructure (PESI), ZooBank, International Plant Names Index (IPNI), EoL, Tropicos and Sandre. These micro-services consistently translate Web APIs responses into RDF graphs utilizing mainly two well-adopted vocabularies: Schema.org <ref type="bibr">(Guha et al. 2015)</ref> and Darwin Core <ref type="bibr">(Baskauf et al. 2015)</ref>. This approach brings about two major advantages. First, the large adoption of Schema.org and Darwin Core ensures that the services can be immediately understood and reused by a large audience within the biodiversity community. Second, wrapping all these Web APIs in SPARQL micro-services "suddenly" makes them technically and semantically interoperable, since they all represent resources (taxa, habitats, traits, etc.) in a common manner. Consequently, the integration task is simplified: confronting data from multiple sources essentially consists of writing the appropriate SPARQL queries, thus making easier web application development and maintenance. We present several concrete cases in which we use this approach to detect disagreements between TAXREF and the aforementioned data sources, with respect to taxonomic information (author, synonymy, vernacular names, classification, taxonomic rank), habitats, bibliographic references, species interactions and life traits.</p></div>			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Michel F et al   </p></note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Presenting author</head><p>Franck Michel </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Presented at</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
