<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">From blues to rock to jazz : three different web audio tube guitar amplifier simulator plugins</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jerome</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
							<email>lebrun@i3s.unice.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Michel</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
							<email>michel.buffa@univ-cotedazur.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jordan</forename><surname>Sintes</surname></persName>
							<email>jordan.sintes@gmail.com</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">Université Côte d&apos;Azur</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">From blues to rock to jazz : three different web audio tube guitar amplifier simulator plugins</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">06E18DC5D800FB7688DB8F832B689FF7</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.5281/ZENODO.6769408</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:51+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We propose to present a set of web audio plugins specialized in three kinds of sounds…. The first one targets blues / classic rock sounds and proposes a drop down menu with presets that go from clean warm blues like the tones used by BB King, to more classic rock/blues distorted sounds used by Jimmy Hendrix or AC/DC. The second one is aimed to Hi Gain/Metal sounds similar Mesa Boogie type sounds, and the third one is an acoustic guitar simulator (use an electric guitar and get an acoustic folk guitar sound). These plugins are partially available in open source, but the versions we propose to demo are commercialized by our laboratory (French CNRS/SATT Sud-Est) and included in some commercial DAWs.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction and related works</head><p>In 2012, Google Chrome proposed for the first time a low-latency opportunity to get live audio from a microphone or other audio inputs. Soon, Opera, Firefox and Microsoft Edge also implemented this. Chris Wilson's "Input Effects" demo was one of the first to show real-time sound processing effects written with Web Audio, and proposed implementations of famous effects such as delay, distortion, wah, etc. This impressive demo proved that low latency processing was achievable. Getting close to the real sound of an analog guitar amplifier remained nevertheless quite a challenge that Chris Wilson's examples did not fully address.</p><p>Many papers have been written about vacuum-tube guitar amplifiers modeling and about the characteristics of linear and nonlinear distortion effects suited for guitars <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. Two main approaches are usually considered for the simulation of the different parts of a guitar amplifier: one is called the technique of virtual analog aka physical modeling. It consists in processing the electronic schematics using tools like the industry standard SPICE analog circuit simulator to translate the circuit into equations to be solved hopefully in real-time. These general equations are typically nonlinear differential algebraic equations and may be solved using integration methods, roots solver algorithms, and sparse matrix techniques. SPICE can even produce C++ code ready to be executed. However, it is often necessary to make huge simplifications and optimizations to achieve real-time processing. This is particularly the case with the modeling of the vacuum tubes used in guitar amplifiers and their interactions with other parts of the circuitry (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref> for a review of common techniques, and <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> for the method used by authors of the Guitarix.org project).</p><p>Another technique consists in a higher-level emulation, in which "logical" parts are identified (filters, tubes, etc.) and may be emulated manually or by machine learning <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> (as with the Kemper profiler/Guitar Rig 6 from Native Instruments, with Neural DSP's gears or Deepmind's WaveNet music generators) using separate or global, explicit or hidden models to achieve perceptual equivalence.</p><p>When we started to tackle this problem five years ago <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, the separate, explicit approach was clearly the simpler and more adapted one to the Web Audio ecosystem esp. its limitations at the time (e.g. custom processing on audio samples was not usable without introducing latency or glitches, AudioWorklet node was not available). Furthermore, the Web Audio API provides highlevel nodes (such as the WaveShaper node and the biquad filter node) that can be used for an easy, quite accurate modelisation of tubes and filters. Namely, when properly used, waveshaping techniques associated with oversampling and appropriate filtering give quite good results <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. The famous pod XT effect processor by Line 6 relies on such techniques <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>.</p><p>Anyhow, we followed this "perceptual" approach consisting in emulating the different parts of the electronic circuit of this amplifier using Web Audio, implementing the necessary signal processing algorithms using the available API, and finding  adequate solutions to circumvent some limitations specific to the Web browser environment (thread priority, latency, JavaScript API limitations). Finally, we extensively compared (quantitatively and qualitatively) our realization with the state of the art, i.e. native simulations, mostly commercial, written in C++, and not having the constraints of webapps. These results exceeded our expectations. Meanwhile, we went on refining the models used in the simulation, and designed a new framework to reproduce different electronic architectures present in various tube amplifiers found in many musicians' equipment <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref>. We can now simulate for example a Fender, a Vox or a Mesa Boogie amplifier, etc. or even create new original designs. These customizable simulations have been tested by professional guitarists, are being used by music schools on an experimental basis and are the subject of a marketing contract by the CNRS in order to be included as plugins <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">19]</ref> in an online commercial DAW (AmpedStudio.com, see Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>).</p><p>Since 2017, we have been developing Web Audio tube guitar amplifier simulations and tools, including an "amp sim designer" that can generate configurations used by an amp sim plugin engine that facilitates the process of creating end user plugins for musicians. To create each amp sim plugins presented in this demo, we proceeded as followed: we experimented with all the internals of our simulation : preamp, tonestack, power amp, reverb, speaker simulation stages, by adjusting gains, filters, tube types, number of tubes, internal topography of the audio graph, speaker impulse types, etc. Some stages of these plugins might not be based on high level audio nodes, in particular when sample accuracy DSP processing is needed (like in the power amp stage, where a negative feedback loop is present). In that case we used the FAUST DSL to generate WebAssembly code <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">[20]</ref>. In a second step we created the GUI of the plugin, and in a third step we adjusted manually the ranges of the different parameters/knobs, by testing and fine tuning the plugin behavior. The plugins have been developed following the Web Audio Modules 2.0 plugin standard <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">[21]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Sound quality of our simulations</head><p>The plugins we developed can be tried with the AmpedStudio.com DAW (Fig <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref>) by creating a track and by adding in the plugin chain the AmpSim Utility plugin (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>) that is useful for adjusting gains, selecting the left/right channel (as the guitar signal is generally mono), and for activating a WebAssembly multi-channel noise gate., then one of the amplifier simulators, eventually with other audio effects for guitarists.</p><p>It is possible to get a taste of the sound quality provided by these plugins by visiting a web page we prepared with dry guitar sounds and the same sounds recorded with our plugins <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> . Only the plugins from Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref> and Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">3</ref> have been used. In addition, several videos are available online, showing these plugins in action :</p><p>• The Blues Machine : https://youtu.be/iZLTLNierAY   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Settings for the demo</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1 : The AmpSim Utility plugin is useful for adjusting input gain and merging/muting left and right channels. It also includes a multi-channel noise gate.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,130.46,326.44,99.60,117.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2 : guitar amp sim plugins in AmpedStudio DAW</figDesc><graphic coords="2,314.35,343.04,240.05,155.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Figure 3 : the three guitar amplifier simulators WAM plugins</figDesc><graphic coords="3,314.96,287.09,236.79,82.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>plugins in the Wasabi Pedalboard host :</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qYzd5WGEbrM</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell>The Metal Machine: https://youtu.be/4epxLuaVuMQ and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>https://youtu.be/dLDoNquJYbc</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell>These plugins in the AmpedStudio DAW:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=js_YOthpyuo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>•</cell><cell>These</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>The Clean Machine (acoustic guitar simulator, in the video</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the guitar has regular non-piezo pickups):</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>https://youtube.com/shorts/VM_mrTegeVA and</cell></row></table><note><p><p><p><p><p><p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rViUD9VWFFM</p>These plugins are now commercialized by our laboratory. They can be seen as "premium versions with extra features" of other open source projects we already published</p><ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b16">[17]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b17">[18]</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b18">[19]</ref></p>. For example, the Amp Designer that has been used for designing these plugins, as well as a previous version of the Blues Machine amp simulator (named Distortion Machine) plugin are available as open source projects</p>2 </p>and you can see other videos of these versions 3 .</p></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>GarageBand amp simulations and withGuitarix, an open source native amp simulator. The referenced papers contain user evaluations showing that the sound quality, latency and feeling guitar in hands of these simulations are comparable to the state of the art from the native world. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-NdMdJQx2Bw (amp designer, useful to create new amp sim plugins, https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zBhn7odezUQ (dynamic transfer curves adjustment for tubes, for simulating tube nonlinear temporal behavior), https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CPDgbRpLcBM (lowlatency + very fast hi-gain demo with live guitar playing)</figDesc><table /><note><p>Our simulation can be played real-time with a real guitar. As of today, we recommend for the best experience to use MacOS and a low latency sound card. By using a real guitar, we propose to compare our Web Audio based tube amp simulation with native simulations such as Guitar Rig by Native Instruments (used by many musicians and guitarists), with</p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>http://mainline.i3s.unice.fr/distortionBook/sounds/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"><p>https://github.com/webaudiomodules/wam-examples, and https://mainline.i3s.unice.fr/AmpSim5/</p></note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2"><p>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PiOD7n3g-Qs (demo of higains distortion in our amp simulations), https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DUM99xQt5fg and https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lIfm9ZMtG-I (professional guitar players using the amp sim),</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			
			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">G2 Workshops and tutorials: Waveshaping and distortion</title>
		<ptr target="https://rhordijk.home.xs4all.nl/G2Pages/Distortion.htm" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-12">Dec. 2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A review of digital techniques for modeling vacuum-tube guitar amplifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pakarinen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Music Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">33</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="100" />
			<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the robustness of the iterative solver in state-space modeling of guitar distortion circuitry</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Van Walstijn</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 18th Int. Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-15)</title>
		<meeting>18th Int. Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-15)<address><addrLine>Trondheim, Norway</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-12">2015, Dec.</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">DESC9115: Digital Audio Systems-Final Project Overdrive/Distortion</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/2123/7608" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
			<pubPlace>Sydney, Australia</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Repository of Tech. Reports</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-time guitar tube amplifier simulation using an approximation of differential equations</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Macak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Schimmel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 13th International Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-10)</title>
		<meeting>13th International Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-10)<address><addrLine>Graz, Austria</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010-09">2010, Sep.</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical methods for simulation of guitar distortion circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Abel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vladimirescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Music Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="42" />
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Audio anecdotes: Tools, tips, and techniques for digital audio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Difilippo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Greenebaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004">2004</date>
			<publisher>AK Peters</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Natick, MA, USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discretization of the&apos;59 Fender Bassman tone stack</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. 9th Int. Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-06)</title>
		<meeting>9th Int. Conference on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-06)<address><addrLine>Montreal, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006-09">2006, Sep.</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Real-time digital simulation of guitar amplifiers as audio effects</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Macak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
			<pubPlace>Czech Republic</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>TU Brno</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Black-Box modelling of nonlinear audio circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Rollo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
			<pubPlace>Finland</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Aalto University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">MSc Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Block-oriented modeling of distortion audio effects using iterative minimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Eichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-15)</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-15)<address><addrLine>Trondheim, Norway</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015">2015</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Block-oriented gray box modeling of guitar amplifiers</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Eichas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Möller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Zölzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Int. Conf. on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-17)</title>
		<meeting>Int. Conf. on Digital Audio Effects (DAFx-17)<address><addrLine>Edinburgh, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Nonlinear modeling of the guitar signal chain enabling its real-time emulation</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schmitz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<pubPlace>Belgium</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>University of Liege</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">PhD Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real-Time guitar amplifier emulation with deep learning</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Wright</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E.-P</forename><surname>Damskägg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Juvela</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Välimäki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Appl. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">766</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Numerical methods for simulation of guitar distortion circuits</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Abel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Vladimirescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Smith</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Music Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Real time tube guitar amplifier simulation using WebAudio</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>⟨hal- 01589229⟩</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2017)</title>
		<meeting>Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2017)<address><addrLine>London, UK</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WebAudio virtual tube guitar amps and pedal board design</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>⟨hal-01893781⟩</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc. Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)</title>
		<meeting>Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)<address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">WAP: Ideas for a Web Audio plug-in standard</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleimola</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Larkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Pellerin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Letz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>⟨hal-01893660⟩</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)</title>
		<meeting>Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)<address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Guitarists will be happy: guitar tube amp simulators and FX pedals in a virtual pedal board, and more!</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>⟨hal-01893681⟩</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proc Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)</title>
		<meeting>Web Audio Conference (WAC&apos;2018)<address><addrLine>Berlin, Germany</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018-09">2018. September. 2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using Faust DSL to develop custom, sample accurate DSP code and audio plugins for the Web browser</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Letz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Orlarey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Michon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Fober</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lebrun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>⟨hal-03087763⟩</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Audio Eng. Soc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">68</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="703" to="716" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Web Audio Modules 2.0, an open Web Audio plugin standard</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Buffa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Ren</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Companion Proceedings (Developer&apos;s track) of the The Web Conference 2022 (WWW &apos;22, ranked A*)</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Lyon, France</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022-04">April 2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Accepted, to be presented</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
