<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Non-Redundant Link Keys in RDF Data: Preliminary Steps</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nacira</forename><surname>Abbas</surname></persName>
							<email>nacira.abbas@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Lorraine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Loria</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-54000</postCode>
									<settlement>Nancy</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Alexandre</forename><surname>Bazin</surname></persName>
							<email>alexandre.bazin@loria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Lorraine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Loria</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-54000</postCode>
									<settlement>Nancy</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jérôme</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
							<email>jerome.david@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université Grenoble Alpes</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit4">Grenoble INP</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit5">LIG</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>F-38000</postCode>
									<settlement>Grenoble</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Amedeo</forename><surname>Napoli</surname></persName>
							<email>amedeo.napoli@loria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Université de Lorraine</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Loria</addrLine>
									<postCode>F-54000</postCode>
									<settlement>Nancy</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Non-Redundant Link Keys in RDF Data: Preliminary Steps</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5A6B5D3808BBD5C7068BEC6CA4E164FE</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:48+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Linked Data</term>
					<term>RDF</term>
					<term>Link Key</term>
					<term>Formal Concept Analysis</term>
					<term>Pattern Structures</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A link key between two RDF datasets D1 and D2 is a set of pairs of properties allowing to identify pairs of individuals, say x1 in D1 and x2 in D2, which can be materialized as a x1 owl:sameAs x2 identity link. There exist several ways to mine such link keys but no one takes into account the fact that owl:sameAs is an equivalence relation, which leads to the discovery of non-redundant link keys. Accordingly, in this paper, we present the link key discovery based on Pattern Structures (PS). PS output a pattern concept lattice where every concept has an extent representing a set of pairs of individuals and an intent representing the related link key candidate. Then, we discuss the equivalence relation induced by a link key and we introduce the notion of non-redundant link key candidate.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>In this paper, we are interested in data interlinking which goal is to discover identity links across two RDF datasets over the web of data <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. The same real world entity can be represented in two RDF datasets by different subjects in RDF triples (subject,property,value) (instead of "object" usually used in RDF data we will use "value"). It is important to be able to detect such identities, for example using rules expressing sufficient conditions for two subjects to be identical. A link key takes the form of two sets of pairs of properties associated with a pair of classes. The pairs of properties express sufficient conditions for two subjects, from the associated pair of classes, to be the same. An example of a link key is A link key can be understood as a "closed set" in the sense that it is maximal w.r.t. the set of pairs of individuals to which it applies. This was firstly discussed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> and then extended in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. Hence the question of relying on Formal Concept Analysis (FCA <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>) to discover link keys is straightforward as FCA is based on a closure operator. Then, given two RDF datasets, FCA is applied in <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> to a binary table where rows correspond to pairs of individuals and columns to pairs of properties. The intent of a concept is a link key candidate which should be validated thanks to suitable quality measures. The extent of the concept is the set of identity links between individuals. Furthermore, a generalization of the former approach proposed in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> is based on pattern structures <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and takes into account different pairs of classes at the same time in the discovery of link keys.</p><p>Link key candidates over two RDF datasets have to generate different and maximal link sets. However it appears that two different link key candidates may generate the same link set. This means that there exists some redundancy between the two link key candidates, that they should be considered as equivalent and merged. This can be achieved by looking at owl:sameAs which is an equivalence relation stating that two individual should be identified. The owl:sameAs relation generates partitions among pairs of individuals that can be used to detect redundant link key candidates and thus reduce their number, i.e., two candidates relying on the same partition are declared as redundant and thus merged.</p><p>In this paper, we present the discovery of link key candidates within the framework of pattern structure. Then, we introduce the notion of non-redundant link key candidate based on the equivalence relation induced by a link key candidate. Finally, we discuss how these candidates can be merged to reduce the search space of link keys.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Basics and Notations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">RDF data</head><p>In this work, we deal with RDF datasets which are defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Definition 1 (RDF dataset).</formula><p>Let U be a set of IRIs (Internationalized Resource Identifier), B a set of blank nodes and L a set of literals. An RDF dataset is a set of triples</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(s, p, v) ∈ (U ∪ B) × U × (U ∪ B ∪ L).</formula><p>Given a dataset D, we denote by: </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">-I(D) = {s | ∃p, v (s, p, v) ∈ D} the set of individual identifiers, -P (D) = {p | ∃s, v (s, p, v) ∈ D}</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">p2 q 2 p2 q 2 p1 q1 p2 q2 p 1 q1 p1 q1 p 2 q2 q2 p 3 q3 p 4 q4 p 3 q 3 p 4 q 4 c1 c2 D1 D2</formula><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Example of two RDF datasets. On the left-hand side, the dataset D1 is populated with instances of the class c1, and on the right-hand side the dataset D2 is populated with instances of the class c2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Link Keys</head><p>Link keys are logical constructors allowing to deduce identity links (owl:sameAs).</p><p>In this paper we will call link key expression the syntactic formulation of a link key, when we do not know whether the expression is a valid link key. For example, the link key expression (i) for all (p, q) ∈ Eq, p(a) = q(b) and p(a) = ∅, (ii) for all (p, q) ∈ In \ Eq, p(a) ∩ q(b) = ∅.</p><p>A link key expression k 1 = (Eq 1 , In 1 , (c 1 , c 2 )) is a link key candidate if:</p><p>(iii) L(k 1 ) = ∅, (iv) k 1 is maximal i.e. there does not exist another link key expression k 2 = (Eq 2 , In 2 , (c 1 , c 2 )) such that Eq 1 ⊂ Eq 2 , In 1 ⊂ In 2 , and</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">L(k 1 ) = L(k 2 ).</formula><p>The number of link key expressions may be exponential w.r.t. the number of properties. Then link key discovery algorithms only consider link key candidates which are link key expressions generating at least one link and that are maximal w.r.t. the set of links they generate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Link Key Discovery</head><p>Here after we assume that all link key expressions are defined on the same pair of datasets D 1 and D 2 w.r.t. one pair of classes, yielding link key expressions of the form k = (Eq, In, (c 1 , c 2 )). In the following, we show how link keys may be discovered within the formalism of pattern structures (see details in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>) and then we discuss the notion of non-redundant link keys.</p><p>Example 1. Let us consider the pattern structure (G, (E, ), δ) displayed in Table 1. Here we skip the details for building this table and the related PS lattice which can be found in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>The rows termed "PS objects" correspond to the set of objects G of the pattern structure and include pairs of related instances. The set of descriptions (E, ) includes all possible pairs of properties preceded either by ∀ or ∃. The mapping δ relates a pair of instances (a, b) ∈ I(c 1 ) × I(c 2 ) to a description as follows: (i) δ(a, b) includes ∀(p, q) whenever p(a) = q(b) and p(a) = ∅, (ii) δ(a, b) includes ∃(p, q) whenever p(a) ∩ q(b) = ∅. Then the descriptions correspond to link key expressions (Eq, In) w.r.t. the pairs of classes (c 1 , c 2 ). It should be noticed that it is possible to simultaneously work with several pairs of classes as explained in <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>.</p><p>We have that δ(a</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">1 , b 1 ) = {∃(p 1 , q 1 ), ∃(p 2 , q 2 )} because p 1 (a 1 ) ∩ q 1 (b 1 ) = ∅ and p 2 (a 1 ) ∩ q 2 (b 1 ) = ∅ while δ(a 2 , b 1 ) = {∃(p 1 , q 1 )} because p 1 (a 2 ) ∩ q 1 (b 1 ) = ∅. Then δ(a 1 , b 1 ) δ(a 2 , b 1 ) = {∃(p 1 , q 1 )} and thus δ(a 2 , b 1 ) δ(a 1 , b 1</formula><p>). This can be read in the pattern concept lattice where the pattern concept pc 5 is subsumed by the pattern concept pc 4 , i.e., the extent of</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">pc 5 {(a 1 , b 1 ), (a 2 , b 2 ), (a 3 , b 3 )} is included in the extent of pc 4 {(a 1 , b 1 ), (a 2 , b 1 ), (a 2 , b 2 ), (a 3 , b 3 )}, while the intent {∃(p 1 , q 1 )} of pc 4 is included in the intent of pc 5 , {∃(p 1 , q 1 ), ∃(p 2 , q 2 )}.</formula><p>The set of all pattern concepts is organized within the pattern concept lattice lkps-lattice displayed in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>. Moreover, all potential link key candidates are lying in the intents of the pattern concepts in the lattice. The corresponding set of link key candidates is denoted by lkc.</p><p>PS objects (g)</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">descriptions (δ(g)) (a1, b1) {∃(p1, q1), ∃(p2, q2)} (a1, b2) {∃(p2, q2)} (a2, b1) {∃(p1, q1)} (a2, b2) {∃(p1, q1), ∃(p2, q2)} (a3, b3) {∀(p1, q1), ∃(p1, q1), ∃(p2, q2)} (a4, b4) {∀(p3, q3), ∃(p3, q3)} (a4, b5) {∀(p4, q4), ∃(p4, q4)} (a5, b4) {∀(p4, q4), ∃(p4, q4)} (a5, b5) {∀(p3, q3), ∃(p3, q3)}</formula><p>Table <ref type="table">1</ref>. The pattern structure related to link key discovery over c1 and c2 introduced in Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>. Let us consider the so-called lkps-lattice and pc = (L(k), k) a pattern concept, where the extent L(k) corresponds to the set of links generated by k, and the intent k corresponds to a link key candidate. Let I denotes the set of instances I = I(c 1 ) ∪ I(c 2 ) and the binary relation k ⊆ I × I such as (a, b) ∈ L(k) → a k b. The interpretation of a k b is: "k states that there exists a owl:sameAs relation between a and b". Actually k is an equivalence relation based on the fact that owl:sameAs itself is an equivalence relation. We say that k induces the equivalence relation k over I. Moreover k forms a partition over I where each element of this partition is an equivalence class. In fact the k equivalence relation will help us to build more concise set of link key candidates since it allows to identify non-redundant link key candidates termed nr-lkc. A link key candidate k 1 is a nr-lkc in lkc if there is no other candidate k 2 in lkc such that k1 and k2 form the same partition. Otherwise, k 1 is redundant.</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">I(c 1 ) × I(c 2 ) ∅ pc 0 {(a 4 , b 5 ), (a 5 , b 4 )} k 1 = {∀(p 4 , q 4 ), ∃(p 4 , q 4 )} pc 1 {(a 4 , b 4 ), (a 5 , b 5 )} k 2 = {∀(p 3 , q 3 ), ∃(p 3 , q 3 )} pc 2 {(a 1 , b 1 ), (a 1 , b 2 ), (<label>a</label></formula><p>In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">2</ref>, it can be observed that k3 and k4 form the same partition, namely {(a 1 , b 1 , a 2 , b 2 ), (a 3 , b 3 )} (it should be noticed that singletons are omitted for the sake of readability). Then the link key candidates k 3 and k 4 are redundant. By contrast, k 1 is a nr-lkc because there is no other candidate k in lkc such that k1 and k form the same partition.</p><p>Let us briefly explain how k3 and k4 are inducing the same partition, namely {(a One main straightforward application of identifying nr-lkc is the ability to reduce the search space of link keys since the set of nr-lkc is included in lkc. Indeed, this can be seen as a refinement where redundant link key candidates inducing the same partition are merged. For example, since k3 and k4 form the same partition, then, k 3 and k 4 can be merged into a nr-lkc k 34 = {k 3 , k 4 }. Among the perspectives is to consolidate the theory and practice of link key discovery based on partition pattern structures initially introduced for mining functional dependencies in <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>{(designation, title)}, {(designation, title), (creator, author)}, (Book, Novel)) which states that whenever an instance a of the class Book has the same (non empty) values for the property designation as an instance b of the class Novel for the property title (universal quantification), and that a and b share at least one value for the properties creator and author (existential quantification), then a and b denote the same entity, i.e., an owl:sameAs relation can be established between a and b.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the set of property identifiers, -C(D) = {c | ∃s (s, rdf:type, c) ∈ D} the set of class identifiers. A triple (s, rdf:type, c) means that the subject s is an instance of the class c. -I(c) = {s | (s, rdf:type, c) ∈ D} the set of instances of c ∈ C(D), p(s) = {v | (s, p, v) ∈ D} is the set of values (or "RDF objects") related to s through p. An identity link is an RDF triple (a, owl:sameAs, b) stating that the IRIs a and b refer to the same real-world entity. Fig. 1 represents two RDF datasets D 1 and D 2 , where P (D 1 ) = {p 1 , p 2 , p 3 , p 4 } and P (D 2 ) = {q 1 , q 2 , q 3 , q 4 }. Then C(D 1 ) = {c 1 } and C(D 2 ) = {c 2 } with I(c 1 ) = {a 1 , a 2 , a 3 , a 4 , a 5 } and I(c 2 ) = {b 1 , b 2 , b 3 , b 4 , b 5 }. For example, the set of values of b 3 for the property q 2 is q 2 (b 3 ) = {v 8 , v 9 }.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Definition 2 (</head><label>2</label><figDesc>({}, {(nbrOfPages, nbrOfBeds)}, (Book, Hospital)) will not satisfy the link key semantics since an instance of class Book and an instance of class Hospital cannot represent the same entity since Book and Hospital are disjoint classes. Link key expression, link key candidate). Let D 1 and D 2 be two RDF datasets, k = (Eq, In, (c 1 , c 2 )) is a link key expression (over D 1 and D 2 ) iff In ⊆ P (D 1 ) × P (D 2 ), Eq ⊆ In, c 1 ∈ C(D 1 ) and c 2 ∈ C(D 2 ). The set of links L(k) (directly) generated by k is the set of pairs of instances (a, b) ∈ I(c 1 ) × I(c 2 ) satisfying:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>3 { 4 {(a 1 5 {(a 3 , b 3 )} k 6 = 6 ∅P (D 1 ) 7 Fig. 2 .</head><label>3415366172</label><figDesc>Fig.2. The pattern concept intents in the pattern concept lattice lkps-lattice include the complete set of link key candidates.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1 , b 1 , a 2 , b 2 ), (a 3 , b 3 )}. The extent of k 3 in lkps-lattice is given by {(a 1 , b 1 ), (a 1 , b 2 ), (a 2 , b 2 ), (a 3 , b 3 )}. By transitivity and symmetry of owl:sameAs, we have that (a 1 , b 2 ) and (b 2 , a 2 ) yields (a 1 , a 2 ), then (a 2 , a 1 ) and (a 1 , b 1 ) yields (a 2 , b 1 ), and finally (b 1 , a 2 ) and (a 2 , b 2 ) yields (b 1 , b 2 ) and the complete graph between (a 1 , a 2 , b 1 , b 2 ). The same thing applies when we consider k 4 instead of k 3 . This intuitively shows how k3 and k4 are inducing the same partition.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discovery of link keys in RDF data based on pattern structures: Preliminary steps</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Abbas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Napoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="CEUR-WS.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ICFCA. CEUR Workshop Proceedings</title>
		<meeting>ICFCA. CEUR Workshop Proceedings</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2668</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="246" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data interlinking through robust linkkey extraction</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atencia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Euzenat</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ECAI</title>
		<meeting>ECAI</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="15" to="20" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Link key candidate extraction with relational concept analysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Atencia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>David</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Euzenat</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Napoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Vizzini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete applied mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">273</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="2" to="20" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Characterizing functional dependencies in formal concept analysis with pattern structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Baixeries</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaytoue</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Napoli</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Mathematics and Artificial Intelligence</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">72</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="149" />
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Data Linking for the Semantic Web</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Ferrara</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nikolov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Scharffe</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Semantic Web and Information Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="46" to="76" />
			<date type="published" when="2011">2011</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pattern Structures and Their Projections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ganter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Kuznetsov</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the International Conference on Conceptual Structures (ICCS)</title>
		<meeting>the International Conference on Conceptual Structures (ICCS)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001">2001</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2120</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="142" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Ganter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Wille</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Formal Concept Analysis: Mathematical Foundations</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999">1999</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A survey of current link discovery frameworks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Nentwig</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Hartung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ngonga Ngomo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Rahm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.3233/SW-150210</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.3233/SW-150210" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Semantic Web</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="419" to="436" />
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
