<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Semantic Indexing of Open Scientific Literature to Help Users Discover and Navigate through Publications Networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2022-08-23">23 Aug 2022</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Franck</forename><surname>Michel</surname></persName>
							<email>franck.michel@inria.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anne</forename><surname>Toulet</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Anna</forename><surname>Bobasheva</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marie-Claude</forename><surname>Deboin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Sébastien</forename><surname>Dupré</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Aline</forename><surname>Menin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marco</forename><surname>Winckler</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andon</forename><surname>Tchechmedjiev</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University Cote d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">CNRS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">Inria</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sophia-Antipolis</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">CIRAD</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Montpellier</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">| University Cote d&apos;Azur</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit3">CNRS</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Sophia Antipolis</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Euromov Digital Health in Motion</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Univ Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">IMT Mines Ales</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Ales</settlement>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Semantic Indexing of Open Scientific Literature to Help Users Discover and Navigate through Publications Networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2022-08-23">23 Aug 2022</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">167AC2E03BDA26A3E5E35D59573803D3</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.3897/biss.6.93640</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received: 18 Aug 2022</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:44+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>In recent years, several evolutions have drastically transformed the way researchers as well as scientific and technical information (STI) services interact with scientific literature. The amount and pace of publications are skyrocketing, whether in journals and conferences or through pre-publication repositories (e.g., arxiv.org), such that it is increasingly difficult to keep up, find and make sense of relevant articles. Furthermore, the specialization of research communities makes it difficult to discover cross-disciplinary knowledge, which is essential to meet the growing demand of funding agencies for interdisciplinary projects. Scientific open archives are central in this landscape, however the keyword-based search services that they usually provide fail to grasp the semantic relationships between articles. Therefore, it is necessary to develop new tools that allow users to find their way in this mass of knowledge.</p><p>In this talk, we wish to present the methods, tools and services implemented in the ISSA* project to address these needs, and discuss how they could fit and be deployed in the</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>biodiversity area. Guided by the open science goals and embracing the FAIR* principles, the project aims to:</p><p>1.</p><p>provide a generic, transferable and extensible pipeline for the analysis and processing of the articles of an open scientific archive; 2.</p><p>turn the processing results into a semantic index stored and published as a public RDF knowledge graph; 3.</p><p>develop innovative search and visualization services that leverage this semantic index to allow researchers, decision makers or STI professionals to explore thematic association rules, networks of co-publications, articles with co-occurring topics, etc.</p><p>The semantic index construction process involves several artificial intelligence techniques: natural language processing, knowledge engineering and Semantic Web. These techniques are used to process the publications' metadata and text to automatically extract thematic descriptors and named entities. These descriptors and named entities are linked to knowledge bases such as Wikidata, DBpedia and GeoNames, or domain-specific terminological resources suited to the archive's domain. The semantic index linked with the third-party resources serves as a keystone to support the development of rich search and visualization tools aimed at researchers and/or STI professionals. What are the research topics that frequently co-occur with climate change, and how do these topics evolve through the years? What public policies frequently occur in articles that mention endangered species? Furthermore, the pipeline could be extended by including existing third-party tools to carry out e.g., the extraction of relationships between entities or the reconciliation of authors' names.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Keywords</head><p>data indexing, knowledge graph, data visualization, scientific archive</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Presenting author</head><p>Franck Michel Exploration of the relationship between concepts health and climate change or any of their sub-concepts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Presented at</head><note type="other">TDWG 2022</note></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1. Association rule stating that articles mentioning concepts COVID-19 and food security (a) also frequently mention the pandemics concept (b).</figDesc><graphic coords="3,53.19,458.93,300.00,96.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2.</figDesc><graphic coords="4,53.19,57.44,300.00,145.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable ISSA stands for Semantic Indexing of a scientific archive Associated Services</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
