<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PathWays: entity-focused exploration of heterogeneous data graphs</title>
				<funder ref="#_259SFSJ #_sEQv8Br">
					<orgName type="full">unknown</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nelly</forename><surname>Barret</surname></persName>
							<email>nelly.barret@inria.fr</email>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antoine</forename><surname>Gauquier</surname></persName>
							<email>antoine.gauquier@etu.imt-nord-europe.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Institut Mines Télécom</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jia-Jean</forename><surname>Law</surname></persName>
							<email>jia-jean.law@polytechnique.edu</email>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="institution">Ecole Polytechnique</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ioana</forename><surname>Manolescu</surname></persName>
							<email>ioana.manolescu@inria.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Inria</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Institut Polytechnique de Paris</orgName>
								<address>
									<country key="FR">France</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PathWays: entity-focused exploration of heterogeneous data graphs</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9C5C46860166C4E523D118702ECD4860</idno>
					<note type="submission">Submitted on 23 May 2023</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:50+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Data graphs</term>
					<term>Graph exploration</term>
					<term>Information Extraction</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ou non, émanant des établissements d'enseignement et de recherche français ou étrangers, des laboratoires publics ou privés.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Motivation and Problem Statement</head><p>Data graphs, including RDF knowledge graphs, as well as Property Graphs (PGs), are often used to represent and share data. More generally, any structured or semistructured dataset can be viewed as a graph, having: (i) an internal node for each structure element of the original dataset, e.g., relational tuple, XML element or attribute, JSON map or array, URI in an RDF graph; (ii) a leaf node for each value in the dataset, e.g., attribute value in a relational tuple, text node or attribute value in XML, atomic (leaf) value in a JSON document, or literal in RDF. The connections between the data items in the original dataset lead to edges in the graph, e.g. parent-child relationship between XML or JSON nodes, edges connecting each relational tuple node with their attributes, etc. In a relational database, when primary key-foreign key pairs are present, they lead to further edges allowing one tuple, e.g., an Employee, to "point to" the Company tuple representing their employer. This graph view of a dataset has been introduced to support unstructured (keyword-based) search on (semi)structured data, since <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref> and through many follow-up works <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Entity-rich graphs</head><p>Building on this idea of integrating heterogeneous data into graphs, the Connec-tionLens system <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref> has been developed to facilitate, for users lacking IT skills, such as data journalists, the exploration of datasets of various models, including relational/CSV, XML, JSON, RDF, and PGs. ConnectionLens turns any (set of ) datasets into a single graph as outlined above. For instance, the data graph at left in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref> features RDF triples about NASA spacecrafts (labeled edges), and an XML document describing presidents who attended spacecraft launches (tree with labeled node and unlabeled edges). ConnectionLens also includes Information Extraction modules, which extract, from any leaf node in the data graph, Named Entities (People, Locations and Organizations) <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, as well as other types of entities that journalists find interesting: temporal moments (date, time); Web site URIs; email addresses; and hashtags. We designate any of these pieces of information as entities, and we model them as extra nodes, e.g., in the data graph in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, organizations appear on a pink background, people on yellow and locations on green, respectively. Each entity is extracted from a leaf text node, to which it is connected by a dashed edge. When an entity is extracted from more than one text node, the edges connecting it to those nodes increase the connectivity of the graph, e.g., "NASA" extracted from the nodes with IDs 15 and 17.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Entity paths</head><p>Journalists are interested in the paths connecting entities in a given dataset. For instance, in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, they may want to know "how people are connected to places". Similarly, an article describes French real estate bought by family members of dictators abroad; here, journalists ask "what are the paths between people and cities (where real estate is)?". Importantly, we should consider paths irrespective of the direction of the edges in the data graph. This is because, depending on how the data is modeled, we may encounter <ref type="figure">-----→ c</ref>; both paths are interesting. Goal: efficient exploration of entity connections Journalist questions such as those above ask for data paths ending in entity pairs of certain kinds. When shown the set of corresponding labeled paths, users may pick one to further explore: how many pairs of entities are connected by each path? which entities are most frequent, e.g., in which cities are most properties located? how do the cities spread across countries, etc. Such analysis requires materializing the entity pairs connected by the paths, which may be very costly, if (i) the graph is large, and/or (ii) there are many paths (the latter is almost always true, especially since our paths may traverse edges in both directions. To mitigate this problem, PathWays includes a materialized view recommender and view-based rewriting module (Sec. 2), which significantly improve performance. Thus, PathWays enumerates paths between entities of user-selected types, (i) independently of the edge direction, (ii) asking for user input to focus on the paths most useful to them, and (iii) efficiently. To our knowledge, PathWays is the first system built for this flavor of graph exploration (see also Sec. 4).</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">x boughtProperty ----------→ y locatedIn ------→ c, or x hasOwner ← ------y locatedIn -</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Demonstration scenarios</head><p>PathWays is developed in Java 11, on top of <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">5]</ref> which build the data and, respectively, the collection graph (see below), and store them in PostgreSQL.</p><p>User interaction with PathWays starts by making some choices: "Which types of entities to connect?" (in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, organizations and people); "How many paths to enumerate?" (say, 20) and "What is the maximum allowed length for a path?" (say, 10). In Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, four paths connect organizations and people; two are shown in yellow and red highlight. Computing the paths on large data graph may be costly. Instead, PathWays leverages a collection graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, a (much smaller) summary of the data graph, grouping similar data nodes in a single collection node, e.g., the spacecraft nodes 10 and 14 in the data graph are grouped in collection C1. For each collection of nodes having text children, e.g., C8 labeled name, the collection of these text children is denoted, e.g., name#; entities (people, locations, etc.) are extracted from such texts. Any path in the data graph also exists in the collection graph, thus PathWays enumerates paths on the smaller collection graph. Each path is then translated in a query over the data graph, to obtain data paths between actual entities. PathWays displays sample entity pairs connected by each path, e.g., Nixon is connected to NASA because he attended a launch involving N. Armstrong. Users can then apply more aggregation/analysis on the entity pairs, look for frequent entities, etc. We will also show how PathWays optimizes path evaluation (see below). We will use real-life datasets, such as PubMed, the NASA dataset, RDF benchmarks, and GeoNames, to investigate connections between people and organizations, e.g., companies funding PubMed article authors, geographic repartition of papers (PubMed) and launches (NASA), etc. A preview of our demonstration can be found at https://team.inria.fr/cedar/projects/abstra/pathways/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">View materialization and view-based rewriting</head><p>When the data graph is large, paths are long, and/or many, evaluating path queries on the graph may be inefficient, despite the graph being extensively in-dexed. However, as illustrated at right in Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>, paths may overlap, e.g., the edges connecting C1, C6 and C7 are common between the two highlighted paths. Leveraging this observation, PathWays identifies the subpaths common to at least two path queries. Then, with the help of a cost model, based on PostgreSQL's estimations, it materializes the most profitable shared subpath s 1 where profit is: the decrease in the total path evaluation cost if the subpath is materialized and its results used to evaluate the paths enclosing it, minus the cost to materialize the subpath. PathWays then rewrites every path query p 1 1 , . . . , p n1 1 containing s 1 , using it as a materialized view. Then, we remove p 1 1 , . . . , p n1 1 from the path set, and, in a greedy fashion, again look for the most profitable common subpath s 2 for the remaining paths, etc. We stop when no subpath is profitable (materializing it costs more than its cost savings). The complexity of the above view selection algorithm is O(N 2 L + N 3 ), for N paths of length at most L.</p><p>Sample performance saving On the NASA RDF dataset (100.000 triples), we enumerated 100 paths, of length 2 to 8, between locations and people. Evaluating them all took 419 seconds, including 12 that timed-out at 30 seconds. PathWays found 89 common subpaths; 16 were selected by our algorithm, which rewrote 98 path queries using them as materialized views. Materializing the 16 paths took 0.1 second, and the total path query evaluation shrank to 6.93 seconds, a speedup of 60×.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Related work and conclusion</head><p>Many graph exploration methods exist, see, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>. Modern graph query languages such as GPML <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> (no implementation so far) or the JEDI <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> SPARQL extension allow asking for paths between nodes matching some query variables. Other systems interact with users to incrementally build SPARQL queries interesting for them, e.g., <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref> for queries with aggregation. In keyword-based search (KBS, in short) <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">4,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b11">12]</ref>, one asks, e.g., for connections between "Sivel Aliev" (related to the Azeirbadjan president) and "Nice" (where she owns villas). KBS is handy when users know keywords (entities) to search for. Complementing the above, PathWays is focused on identifying and computing all paths between certain extracted entities, to give a first global look at the dataset content, for graphs obtained from multiple data models. For performance, PathWays leverages a compact graph summary and efficiently materializes views; our view materialization problem, focusing only on paths, is a restriction of that considered, e.g., in <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, enabling a low complexity while being very effective. We are currently adapting our algorithm to other graph data management systems.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Fig. 1. Sample data graph (left), and corresponding collection graph (right) on which paths linking entities are explored (highlighted areas).</figDesc><graphic coords="3,134.77,115.84,345.82,70.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><p>Acknowledgments This work has been funded by the <rs type="grantNumber">DIM RFSI PHD 2020-01</rs> project and the <rs type="projectName">AI Chair SourcesSay</rs> (<rs type="grantNumber">ANR-20-CHIA-0015-01</rs>) chair.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
				<org type="funded-project" xml:id="_259SFSJ">
					<idno type="grant-number">DIM RFSI PHD 2020-01</idno>
					<orgName type="project" subtype="full">AI Chair SourcesSay</orgName>
				</org>
				<org type="funding" xml:id="_sEQv8Br">
					<idno type="grant-number">ANR-20-CHIA-0015-01</idno>
				</org>
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Top-K Diversification for Path Queries in Knowledge Graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Aebeloe</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Setty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Montoya</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ISWC Workshops</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">DBXplorer: A system for keyword-based search over relational databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Agrawal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chaudhuri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Das</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICDE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Empowering investigative journalism with graph-based heterogeneous data management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anadiotis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Balalau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Bouganim</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE DEBull</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Graph integration of structured, semistructured and unstructured data for data journalism</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Anadiotis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Balalau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Conceicao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Inf. Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Abstra: toward generic abstractions for data of any model (demonstration)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Barret</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Manolescu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Upadhyay</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CIKM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">ConnectionLens: Finding connections across heterogeneous data sources (demonstration)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chanial</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dziri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Galhardas</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PVLDB</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Graph pattern matching in GQL and SQL/PGQ</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Deutsch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Francis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hare</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Libkin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
			<publisher>SIGMOD</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Keyword proximity search on XML graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Hristidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Papakonstantinou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Balmin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICDE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2003">2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Scalable multi-query optimization for SPARQL</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Le</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kementsietsidis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Duan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ICDE</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012">2012</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Example-driven exploratory analytics over knowledge graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lissandrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">EDBT</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023">2023</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Knowledge graph exploration systems: are we lost?</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lissandrini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Mottin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Hose</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Pedersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="www.cidrdb.org" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">CIDR</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Keyword search on large graphs: A survey</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Sci. Eng</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2021">2021</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
