<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">STMotif Explorer: A Tool for Spatiotemporal Motif Analysis</title>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">FAPERJ</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CAPES</orgName>
				</funder>
				<funder>
					<orgName type="full">CNPq</orgName>
				</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Heraldo</forename><surname>Borges</surname></persName>
							<email>heraldo.borges@cefet-rj.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Cefet</forename><forename type="middle">/</forename><surname>Rj</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Antonio</forename><surname>Castro</surname></persName>
							<email>antonio.castro@eic.cefet-rj.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Fabio</forename><surname>Porto</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Rafaelli</forename><surname>Coutinho</surname></persName>
							<email>rafaelli.coutinho@cefet-rj.br</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Esther</forename><surname>Pacitti</surname></persName>
							<email>esther.pacitti@lirmm.fr</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Eduardo</forename><surname>Ogasawara</surname></persName>
							<email>eogasawara@ieee.org</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">University of Montpellier</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">INRIA</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">STMotif Explorer: A Tool for Spatiotemporal Motif Analysis</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">5B25A6AE28E7FE2FF5A16B3F0B5FBC7D</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-04-12T14:52+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Motif discovery</term>
					<term>Spatial-Time</term>
					<term>Visualization</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Pattern discovery is an important task in time series mining. A pattern that occurs a significant number of times in a time series is called a motif. Several approaches have been developed to discover motifs in time series. However, we can observe a clear gap in exploring the spatial-time series data. It is challenging to understand and characterize the meaning of the motif obtained concerning the data domain, comparing different approaches and analyzing the quality of the results obtained. We propose STMotif Explorer, a spatial-time motif analysis system that aims to interactively discover and visualize spatial-time motifs in different domains, offering insight to users. STMotif Explorer enables users to use and implement novel spatiotemporal motif detection techniques and then run this across various domains. Besides, STMotif Explorer offers the users a set of interactive resources where it is possible to visualize and analyze the discovered motifs and compare the results from different techniques. We show the features of our system with different approaches using real data.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>Pattern discovery has become increasingly challenging in sensor and IoT data <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8]</ref>. In this context, a motif is a particular pattern that we can understand as a subsequence that occurs a significant number of times in time series <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. Relevant time series phenomena present different behaviors when analyzed in space and time. These phenomena are best modeled as space-time series, where each time series is associated with a position in space <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>. In this context, the motifs are specified in space and time and might not be discovered when we only analyze the temporal dimension. Discovering motifs becomes challenging when we look at the spatiotemporal series <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. This problem is challenging for many reasons:</p><p>Traditional approaches are not effective for spatiotemporal data. To find out spatiotemporal motifs, it is necessary to identify regions of space and time in which they are frequent. Traditional approaches are inefficient as they identify motifs only in the temporal dimension, excluding those more spatially distributed. Finding and analyzing spatiotemporal motifs may enable us to understand how the phenomenon behaves <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.</p><p>Lack of spatiotemporal motif discovery tools. Some tools, such as VizTree <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> and GrammarViz <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, were developed for the discovery and visualization of motifs in time series. These tools are not suitable for working with spatiotemporal data. Besides, they are not modular, i.e., they do not enable the development, execution, and comparison of other approaches in the same environment.</p><p>Spatiotemporal motif visualization tools. Discovered spatial-time motifs visualization and their distributions over space and time can bring new insights. Some initiatives work with the spatiotemporal approach to identify motifs in the trajectory data <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> but focus on analyzing moving objects. It excludes works investigating phenomena that occur at each position throughout time, where the sensors are fixed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>preprint</head><p>It is essential to create tools enabling data scientists to interact with spatial-temporal motif discovery systems to address the abovementioned challenges. In this demo, we present STMotif Explorer, a visual tool we developed. In addition to enabling interaction with discovered motifs, the tool provides the user with an interactive process where it is possible to register discovery algorithms following a canonical data structure and execute these with registered data. These features open up several opportunities, enabling us to compare and view motif discovery functions and see the results in the same environment.</p><p>Besides this introduction, the paper is organized into four more sections. Section 2 provides the background. Section 3 describes the STMotif Explorer. Section 4 presents the demonstration scenario. Finally, Section 5 provides the conclusion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Spatiotemporal Motif Discovery and Visualization</head><p>Borges et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> proposed the Combined Series Approach (CSA), i.e., an approach to discover and rank motifs in spatial-time series. CS A is organized in three main steps: (i) normalization &amp; SAX indexing; (ii) discovery of spatialtime motifs; (iii) ranking of spatial-time motifs. CS A is summarized in Algorithm 1. It takes as input a spatial-time series dataset S , a word size w, an alphabet size a, sb and tb corresponding to spatial and temporal block sizes, and spatiotemporal constraints σ and κ.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Algorithm 1 Combined Series Approach 1: function CS A(S , w, a, sb, tb, σ, κ) 2:</formula><p>S ← normS AX(S , a)</p><p>3:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">S T Moti f s ← discoverS T Moti f s(S , w, sb, tb, σ, κ) 4: rS T Moti f s ← rankS T Moti f s(S T Moti f s) 5:</formula><p>return rS T Moti f s</p><p>Visual time series exploration has been extensively studied <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>. However, we find a very restricted bibliography for approaches to motif visualization in space-time series. From them, some missing features are: (i) rank and view space-time motifs to shed light on the most important ones; (ii) compare different approaches over different datasets;</p><p>(iii) evaluate the motifs found compared to ground truths.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">STMotif Explorer</head><p>We developed STMotif Explorer based on the following objectives: (i) spatial-time motifs visualization; (ii) modularity; and (iii) comparison of results. Regarding visualization, the goal is to provide an interactive environment where users can view and explore the motifs discovered in a spatiotemporal dataset. Such interactivity enables a deeper investigation of discovered patterns.</p><p>The modularity enables users to register and execute their spatial-time motif detection and ranking algorithms using a canonical data structure. The tool can view and save the results obtained from this processing. Besides the algorithms, it will also be possible to register new spatiotemporal databases, even those with ground-truth results, which the motif discovery algorithms can use. Finally, the comparison feature lets us view Spatial-Temporal Motif Discovery (STMD) algorithms relative to ground truth data. It can be used for performance comparison in a single environment. The tool provides data visualization and statistics of the results.</p><p>To provide all these features, we designed STMotif Explorer into two main parts depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.a. The API provides the means to register the algorithms and data to the system. Besides enabling the execution of the registered algorithms, the interface provides functionalities for visual interaction with the data and the results. The interface also provides ways to compare the obtained results. The core algorithms behind the tool are implemented using the R language.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">STMotif Explorer: API</head><p>The API enables users to interact with the infrastructure through three components.</p><p>Register Algorithm and Rank Functions. The system architecture is modular, enabling the addition of new algorithms for execution through the interface. The user can register new functions for motif discovery and ranking. The canonical data structure STMotifDS was defined to ease the parameterization of the functions and subsequent comparison of the obtained results. This structure is made up of Motifs information, with the positions of its occurrences MotifPositions, and other information regarding each motif MotifInformation. This information is related to the result of the processing by the algorithm (such as the distance among the occurrences and entropy). Besides these, it is composed of the GenericInformation field, where information used by the algorithm is stored (such as the parameters and dataset reference). The structure is summarized in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">1</ref>.b.</p><p>Register Datasets. An important task for verifying and validating an approach is execution across multiple domains. Users can also register new spatiotemporal datasets that can be used in the execution of registered algorithms through the interface. Besides, it is possible to register files containing the results of other algorithms and with the ground truth results, which can be used through the interface. These files are in RData format and follow the canonical data structure STMotifDS. All files need to be registered, with their signature of the functions, in the file CONFIG.xml to become available by the tool.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">STMotif Explorer: Interface</head><p>The graphical web-based interface (depicted in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2</ref>), also implemented in R and JavaScript, provides how users can run the register algorithms and interact with the data. It has options to run motif discovery algorithms (Run Motif Identification component). After execution, the Load/Save STMD component is invoked to store the results within the system architecture. This section presents the entire process of applying STMotif Explorer in identifying, ranking, and visualizing spatiotemporal motifs in scenarios with real data. Our cases also present the flexibility of the tool, which enables the inclusion of new motif discovery and ranking functions. Also, we present visualization and analysis scenarios of the discovered motifs, comparing different approaches applied in the same domain. This demo uses the seismic spatialtime dataset <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. STMotif Explorer has open source code and a demonstration video that can be obtained through the GitHub repository <ref type="foot" target="#foot_0">1</ref> .</p><p>Scenario 1: API. In this scenario, we present the modularity of the tool by receiving new functions and data. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2A</ref> presents an example of the MPMoti f Discovery() function written in the R language for motif discovery. This function uses the TSMP R package <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>, which implements the Matrix Profile <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>. The Matrix Profile (MP) approach is based on computing the distance of a sequence with the most similar subsequence present in the time series. Two other functions are already provided by the architecture, one for STMD, S earchS T Moti f () and the RankS T Moti f () ranking function, both using the STMotif R Package, which reflects the CS A approach <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. Then the ground truth results of the seismic dataset motifs are recorded to compare the results.</p><p>Scenario 2: Run Motif discovery. Once the functions and datasets are registered, the user can use the functionalities available in the interface to execute the algorithms. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2B</ref> shows the menu to select the dataset, the STMD, and ranking functions. When the user selects the approach to be executed, fields for the parameter values are presented.</p><p>In this scenario, we execute the CS A approach using the default parameter values defined in the API. It uses the RankS T Moti f () ranking function with the seismic dataset. At the end of execution, the tool informs the user about the end of the process. It saves the results in the architecture in an RData format file, following the canonical data structure, and is now available for use in the other features.</p><p>Scenario 3: Data Visualization. Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2C</ref> shows the arrangement of occurrences of the discovered motifs. The user also can iterate with the data at different levels of detail by magnifying the image. It is possible to select a region of space and view only the motifs found in this area. In the menu shown in Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2D</ref>, the discovered motifs are listed, and sorted according to the previous ranking, starting with the best ranking. Each motif represents a set of the same occurrences and is presented in a different color. The user can select a subset of motifs to view through this menu. We choose the information related to the best-ranked motif, its occurrences, and its signal in the space-time series (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2E</ref>).</p><p>Scenario 4: Comparison. It offers users a tool to compare the results of different approaches and the result of one approach with its corresponding ground truth (Figure <ref type="figure" target="#fig_1">2F</ref>). To obtain the result of the MP approach, we performed the motif discovery process of the MPMotifDiscovery function. Then, we compare it with the ground truth. Users can check that the approach is inaccurate, given the statistical results presented in the information table, even with many occurrences discovered. The visualization analysis confirms this argument since it even returns multiple occurrences. They are visibly distant from the correct occurrences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Conclusion</head><p>This paper introduces a Spatial-Temporal Motif Visualization tool, the STMotif Explorer, that effectively addresses the gap of visualized constrained space-time motifs. It provides a comprehensive system for interactive discovery, visualization, and comparative analysis of motifs. The tool enables filtering and ranking of motifs during the visualization and provides ways to explore motifs with ground truth data. This feature helps researchers and practitioners evaluate different algorithms and the quality of discovered motifs in various domains.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Figure 1: STMotif Explorer Architecture (a); STMotifDS Data Structure (b)</figDesc><graphic coords="4,86.04,72.00,252.72,183.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Figure 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Figure 2: Screenshots of STMotif Explorer API and user interface</figDesc><graphic coords="4,72.00,499.44,467.99,127.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0"><p>Available at https://github.com/cefet-rj-dal/STMotifexplorer.</p></note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors thank <rs type="funder">CNPq</rs>, <rs type="funder">CAPES</rs>, and <rs type="funder">FAPERJ</rs> for partially sponsoring this research.</p></div>
			</div>
			<listOrg type="funding">
			</listOrg>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">tsmp: An R Package for Time Series with Matrix Profile</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Bischoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Rodrigues</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">R Journal</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="76" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial-time motifs discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Borges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dutra</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Bazaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Coutinho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Perosi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Porto</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Masseglia</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Pacitti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ogasawara</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Intelligent Data Analysis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1121" to="1140" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<ptr target="https://opendtect.org/osr/Main/NetherlandsOffshoreF3BlockComplete4GB" />
		<title level="m">Netherlands Offshore F3 Block -Complete</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Technical report</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visual exploration of time series anomalies with metro-viz</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Eichmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Tatbul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Solleza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Zdonik</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data</title>
		<meeting>the ACM SIGMOD International Conference on Management of Data</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2019">2019</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1901" to="1904" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">VizTree: a tool for visually mining and monitoring massive time series databases</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Lonardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Lankford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Nystrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Thirtieth international conference on Very large data bases</title>
		<meeting>the Thirtieth international conference on Very large data bases<address><addrLine>Toronto, Canada</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>VLDB Endowment</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004-08">aug 2004</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1269" to="1272" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>VLDB &apos;04</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Matrix profile goes MAD: variable-length motif and discord discovery in data series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Linardi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Palpanas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1022" to="1071" />
			<date type="published" when="2020">2020</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Motif discovery in spatial trajectories using grammar inference</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boedihardjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Frankenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gandhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, Proceedings</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013">2013</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1465" to="1468" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Comprehensive review on time series motif discovery using evolutionary techniques</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Ramanujam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Padmavathi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Journal of Advanced Intelligence Paradigms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1-2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="155" to="170" />
			<date type="published" when="2022">2022</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">GrammarViz 2.0: A tool for grammar-based pattern discovery in time series</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Senin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Lin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Oates</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gandhi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Boedihardjo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Frankenstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lerner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lecture Notes in Computer Science (including subseries Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics)</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014">2014</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8726</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="468" to="472" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Spatial computing</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shekhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Feiner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Aref</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="72" to="81" />
			<date type="published" when="2016">2016</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Survey on time series motif discovery</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Torkamani</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Lohweg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2017">2017</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Time series joins, motifs, discords and shapelets: a unifying view that exploits the matrix profile</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C.-C</forename><surname>Yeh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Ulanova</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Begum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Ding</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Dau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zimmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mueen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Keogh</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="83" to="123" />
			<date type="published" when="2018">2018</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
